<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The amours of Charles Duke of Mantua and Margaret Countess of Rovera· A novel. Translated out of Itallian.</title>
            <title>Amore di Carlo Gonzaga, duca di Mantova, e della contessa Margarita della Rovere. English</title>
            <author>Leti, Gregorio, 1630-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 225 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87913</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1329A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230704</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896433</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896433</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87913)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2408:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The amours of Charles Duke of Mantua and Margaret Countess of Rovera· A novel. Translated out of Itallian.</title>
                  <title>Amore di Carlo Gonzaga, duca di Mantova, e della contessa Margarita della Rovere. English</title>
                  <author>Leti, Gregorio, 1630-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 200 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Herringman, and sold by Jos. Knight and Francis Saunders, at the Blew-Anchor, in the lower walk of the New-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Leti, Gregorio.  L'amore di Carlo Gonzaga, duca di Mantova, e della contessa Margarita della Rovere.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Edition.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Carlo --  II, --  duca di Mantova, 1637-1665 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Della Rovere, Margherita --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:3"/>
            <p>THE AMOURS OF CHARLES DUKE of MANTUA AND MARGARET COUNTESS of ROVERA. A NOVEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of</hi> Itallian.</p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Henry Herringman,</hi> and Sold by <hi>Joſ. Knight</hi> and <hi>Francis Saunders,</hi> at the <hi>Blew-Anchor,</hi> in the Lower walk of the <hi>New-Exchange.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154259:4"/>
            <head>The LOVES of CHARLES DUKE of <hi>MANT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>A;</hi> And of MARGARET Counteſs of <hi>RO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERA:</hi> A <hi>Tranſlation</hi> out of <hi>Italian.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Princeſs <hi>Mary</hi> remaining a Widdow by the Death of the Prince her Husband, imployed all her Art and Care in Governing the <hi>State,</hi> which we may yet call Hers; and us'd much Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in Chuſing fit <hi>Miniſters</hi> to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt Her in that Affair, during the Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154259:5"/>of her Son <hi>Charles,</hi> who was too young to meddle with Affaires of that Nature: I need not here undertake the deſcription of that extreme tender affection which all the World obſerv'd in this Princeſs towards the young Duke; but will recommend it to thoſe fond Women, who are Mothers of an only Son, and ſole Heir to a great and Illuſtrious Family: The Careſſes of this indulgent Mother were more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful upon him, then all the Political, Scholaſtical, and Military inſtructions which he received every day from the different Maſters of his Exerciſes. All the Ladies of the Court, to comply with the deſires of the Dutcheſs (whoſe greateſt pleaſure was, to ſee her Son won by thoſe extraordinary Careſſes,) and to delight themſelves in the great ſatisfaction they every day took in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering new graces in that little Prince, made it their whole ſtudy to pleaſe him, by carreſſing and imbracing him even in their Armes; although he was already in an Age wherein Nature uſually excites thoſe motions which Love often produces. One day one of the Principal Senatours of <hi>Mantua</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154259:5"/>the Ladies that waited on the Dutcheſs, &amp; her Maids of Honour, were thus employ'd about this little Prince, could not refraine from ſaying aloud, That the State would have but an Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate Prince; in which, he proved no falſe Prophet.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all the young Ladies that attended the Dutcheſs, there was one born in the City of <hi>Caſale,</hi> and was, by reaſon of her beauty, and good Meene, juſtly called, The Ornament of the Court, and delight of the Courtiers: The little Duke himſelf expreſſed a great inclination for her, and one may ſay much above what his tender years ſeem'd to permit: but perhaps her name being <hi>Margaret,</hi> this young Prince believed he did nothing below himſelf, in admiring the Jewel, which is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally called the pureſt.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs, who was infinitely pleaſed with what ever her Son de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in, recommended him particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to this young Lady (not as to a Governeſs, her Age being almoſt equal, but onely) to divert him in his houres of Recreation, which was truely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend the Cabbidge to the care of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154259:6"/>the Kid, and to give the Sheep into the keeping of the Wolfe: For, this young Lady looking upon this Imployment as a good Fortune for her, and ſeeing very well that nothing was wanting in this young Prince but the Age to Govern, ſhe ſo well applyed her ſelf to get his Favour, in making uſe of all thoſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Arts that uſually takes young Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that in a little time it was eaſie to be obſerv'd, her Intentions were not ſo much to ſerve him as a Maſter, but to gain him for a Friend; and, to change the quality of Servant into that of his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>The little Duke, who already began to take ſome other kind of delight in the Company of Ladies, then what little Children uſually do, very eaſily ſacrific'd theſe Firſt Fires of his Love, which were newly born in him, to this young and ſubtil Play-fellow of his; who, on her ſide, was more and more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd with Love to this young Prince, by the great and particular kindneſs he expreſt to her.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, whileſt theſe two young hearts burn in a reciprocal Fire for one another, yet their years were ſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154259:6"/>tender, that all their Pleaſures conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Talking, and taking each other by the hand, and perhaps in ſome little ſtolne Kiſſes now and then: All the Diverſions which the Duke found in the Court amongſt the Ladies; being, either to pull down the Stool, when they were ſet to work, or elſe to fling their work into the fire, or ſometime to ſteal a Kiſs, or to jumpe into their Armes, and talk of Love, which he as yet but little underſtood. But Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, which is ſo great a Courtier in the Palaces of all Princes, fail'd not to make an early viſit to the Court of that young Duke, and was already got amongſt all his little Play-fellows, and began already to play the Tyrant in the Hearts of the young Ladies; and, chiefly amongſt thoſe who believed they merited the Dukes Favour moſt; if not in beau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, yet by reaſon of their great Birth, or in the Favour of the Dutcheſs his Mother: yet, neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, the Duke made ſtill his greateſt Court to Madamoiſelle <hi>Margaret;</hi> and, ſhe fail'd not to give him a return; and the more they perceiv'd the envy of the other Ladies, who indeavoured to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154259:7"/>Croſs them, the more powerful their Love grew to each other.</p>
            <p>It was one day told the Dutcheſs, That her Son was ſo taken up with his love to Madamoiſelle <hi>Margaret,</hi> that he would never make the Sign of the Croſs with any Hand but Hers: but the Dutcheſs rallying preſently that Man which told her ſo, Anſwered him; Where there is no Malice, Love is ſincere; Truſting to the innocent Childiſhneſs of ſuch tender years, and not being able to imagine, that a young Child of nine years old (as he was) could have a Paſsion for a Girle of the ſame Age. The Mother of Madamoiſelle <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> liv'd alſo in this Court, and waited upon the Dutcheſs, which was the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of her daughters being there ſo young: This old Lady was ſo crafty, that ſhe wanted nothing but <hi>Poetry</hi> to be that <hi>Coriſco</hi> in the <hi>Paſtor Fido;</hi> the more ſhe diſcover'd ſigns of Love in the Duke to her Daughter, the more ſhe inſtructed her in the Art to increaſe and mannage that growing Paſſion; and Taught her the Art of making Love, which ſhe underſtood in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:154259:7"/>
            <p>In the mean time the Dutcheſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to think it now high time to withdraw her Son from the company of Women, amongſt whom, he ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, like other young Princes, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away the beſt part of the day; ſhe choſe a Governour for him, prudent, and of approved integrity, and indowed with all neceſſary qualifications fit for a man that was to undertake ſo great an Imployment as the Education of a young Prince. The Perſon ſhe made choice of, as moſt fit, was the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Arrigony;</hi> who receiv'd this charge with all the demonſtrations of Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and joy imaginable; hoping, that his Services would in time render him very conſiderable in the Government, by the impreſſions he ſhould make upon the ſpirit of this young Prince; but, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd quite contrary to his expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>When the Dutcheſs committed this young Duke unto the Care of the Marqueſs, ſhe above all recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to him three things:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> To Teach him all the Exerciſes of a Gallant Man with Mildneſs, that he might learn them with delight.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:154259:8"/>To be ſure not to neglect the Finding out what he was chiefly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to, and moſt capable of; leaſt he ſhould give him too hard a Leſſon.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And above all, not to force him to do any thing againſt his will, and was abſolutely againſt his inclination; and to be ſure to allow him his houres of Divertiſements with the Ladies of the Court, and principally with Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>Margaret,</hi> who was chiefly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his Humour.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpeak the Truth, theſe orders were not at all ſutable to the Prudence nor Humour of the Marqueſs; who could not imagine to what end they were given him, ſeeing nothing in them extraordinary; beſides, he was vext within himſelf, to ſee, by that, the Princeſs lookt upon him as a Man very unread in what belong'd to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Prince: He Promis'd never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs to obey her Highneſs exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to be wanting in that fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity which was ſo natural to his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſo particular to himſelf; yet he could not hold from ſaying, That he was very ready to ſerve his Maſter to his capacity; but, in his opinion, it
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154259:8"/>would be better to diſaccuſtome a little this young Prince from the company of Ladies, then to uſe him ſo much to their Converſation; ſince he could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no Leſſons from them but what were Effeminate, which was a thing very injurious to Princes: To which the Dutcheſs reply'd; That the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and lawful converſe with Women taught great Men to Rule with gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that ſhe deſir'd nothing more in her Son, nor from himſelf. The Marqueſs having no more to ſay after that Declaration, made no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers but of Proteſtations of obedience to her Highneſs in all things. After that the Dutcheſs ſent for the young Duke, and commanded him to look upon the Marqueſs as the guide of his Perſon and actions; and perſwaded him to think it no trouble to follow the Adviſes of a Man, who would inſpire no Sentiments into him but thoſe of his Glory and advantage.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs having paid his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects and Acknowledgments to the Dutcheſs, retir'd himſelf till the Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment order'd for him was made ready: In going out of the Hall he met with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154259:9"/>Mounſieur <hi>Pianezza</hi> a Friend of his, and his particular Confident, to whom he related his new happineſs in the Dutcheſſes Favour; withal, telling him the particular Orders he received from her concerning the Education of the young Duke, not forgetting a word of all had paſt, eſpecially that paſſage which concern'd of the young Dukes Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amongſt the Ladies of the Court: <hi>Pianezza</hi> judging this Order not very agreeable to the Marqueſs, whiſper'd to him very ſoftly; Monſieur, Be you ſure to tye the Aſſe where the Maſter bids you, and let the Wolves eat it if they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs anſwer'd, ſmiling; I am too Old to make uſe of opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and too Young to ſerve the Amours of another.</p>
            <p>Madamoiſelle <hi>Margaret,</hi> who knew the humour of the Marqueſs was more inclin'd to Rigour, and Duty, then of Compliance, would not have been trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to have ſeen the Education of her young Duke committed to any other then he; though it is certain ſhe was too young to make this diſtinction of her ſelf, but that ſhe was inſtructed by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154259:9"/>her Mother. Now it happen'd one day, that this young Lady meeting with the Duke and the Marqueſs together, ſhe ſaid (without doubt, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of her Mother) Sir, I am extreame glad to ſee the Choice the Dutcheſs has made of you for the Conduct of our Prince; for certainly, it could have been committed to no perſon in the World ſo fit as your ſelf; whoſe merit is ſo univerſally eſteem'd, and 'tis likely to be moſt profitable for his Highneſs advantage. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs gueſsing from whence this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement came, and that her Mother had taught her what to ſay, could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain from Laughing a-little; and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her by the hand, acknowledg'd her Favour by all the expreſsions he could think of: taking very much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the diſcourſe of that young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who, to ſay truth, beſides her other extraordinary beauties, was very agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in her diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Another time, meeting her in the Court of the Pallace, ſhe told the Marqueſs, almoſt Laughing; Now the Prince is ſo much yours, we can be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd no part in him: The Marqueſs
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154259:10"/>alſo Laughing, and putting his hand upon her Face, anſwered her; My pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty little Lady, the Duke is too young to be yours, therefore you ought not to be angry that he is ſo much mine: Thereupon the young Duke taking Madamoiſelle <hi>Margaret</hi>'s ſide, anſwered preſently, I will be theirs that will be mine; Would you have me be yours? The young Lady only anſwer'd with a low Curt'ſy, and a Look, which ſhew'd the deſires and ſentiments of Her heart.</p>
            <p>Some few Moneths after that, the Marqueſs being Declar'd Governour, and the <hi>Duke of Parma</hi> being to paſs through that Countrey to go to <hi>Venice,</hi> the Dutcheſs, although he intended to make that Voyage Incognito, fail'd not to ſend the Marqueſs, at all adventures to meet him, with her young Son the Duke; and the Dutcheſs deſiring, that he ſhould be received in paſſing by, with all the Honours imaginable, though he intended not to be known: The Complemental diſpute between theſe two Princes at this Ceremonious Enterview, kept them ſo long in the hot Sun in the Fields, that the young
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154259:10"/>Duke received no little trouble by the heat which is ſo ordinary there in the Moneth of <hi>June:</hi> In the mean time all things having pleas'd the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> very much in this meeting, and the young Duke returning home, he fell into a little Feaver, accompanied with ſo great a pain in his head, that it was the trouble of the whole Court, eſpecially the Dutcheſs, who was moſt ſenſibly afflicted; no Remedies imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable for his diſtemper were omitted, yet nevertheleſs they did no good, for the Feaver and extreame pain in his head rather increaſed; although Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>Margaret,</hi> whoſe grief was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to her tenderneſs, ſtirr'd not from his Bed-ſide; laying her hand ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon his head, which was no ſmall pleaſure and eaſe to the young ſick Prince. The Dutcheſs his Mother, who was almoſt every day coming and going to his Chamber, to inquire of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, asking him one day, How he did? he anſwer'd her boldly; Madam, ever ſince Madamoiſelle <hi>Margaret</hi> has toucht my head, I have ſcarce felt any Paine. It was not very difficult for the Mother to believe her Son, from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154259:11"/>obſervation ſhe had already made of his Love to that young Lady, and therefore ſhe ſaid to him, Well, my ſon, ſhe ſhall be put to bed to you, if the Marquis your Governour will approve of it; He will not approve of it, (replied the yong Prince) becauſe he does not know my diſeaſe: I do know it ſaid the Marquis, (who was not very far off) and I know that your ſickneſs has need of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy.</p>
            <p>During this ſickneſs of three or four days the hearts of this <hi>Piramus,</hi> and of this <hi>This be</hi> inflam'd extreamly, but in a way very natural and conformable to their age, which did not yet allow them any other thoughts but what were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent; This young Lady, who was not leſs intereſſed in the repoſe of the Prince than of his health, ſtirr'd not from his bed-ſide from morning until night, with a Fan in her hand to drive away the Flyes, which in that Countrey ordinarily torments the ſick.</p>
            <p>He being at laſt recovered from this fit of ſickneſs, applyed himſelf anew to his exerciſes, though with little inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or profit; The Marquis ſaw very well that the love which this young
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154259:11"/>Prince had for this <hi>Madamoiſelle Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> grew up with him, and that his deſires of profiting in Learning thoſe things more fit for his Study (without which a Prince looſes his beſt orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) diminiſht every day as he grew older, which was a moſt ſenſible afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Marquis, who took all the pains imaginable about him.</p>
            <p>One evening after Supper the Dutcheſs walking in her Garden with the Marquis, ſhe askt him the reaſon why her ſon made ſo ſlow a Progreſs in thoſe exerciſes he had learnt, as well Military as others, and wondred that at 14 years of age as he was then, there was nothing at all extraordinary to be obſerv'd in him. The Marqueſs fancy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the aſtoniſhment the Dutcheſs had put on was a reproach to his diligence and affection both, was very much piqu'd, and a little mortified, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs without diſcovering his reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; Me thinks, Madam, ſaid he, if I may have leave to ſay ſo to your Highneſs, that your Speeches are very much alter'd from your declar'd opinion to me that minute your Highneſs was pleas'd to give me that honourable im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154259:12"/>of Governour to the young Duke your ſon; For, I remember you commanded me then, to inſtruct him in all things with mildneſs and moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and now your Highneſs wonders why I have not forc'd his nature, and his ſtrength. I confeſs, Madam, I ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled nothing more than diſobeying your Orders, but to deal ingeniouſly with your Highneſs, I muſt tell you this truth, that if my affection to him and my cares had not rous'd him a little, and almoſt conſtrain'd him to apply. himſelf to thoſe exerciſes the moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him, that he would this day be more ignorant than he is; although whatever he poſſeſſes appears very inconſiderable to your Highneſs, the Duke can ſit very well, and has a very becoming grace on horsback, he has often ran at the ring and won the Prize, to the ſhame and confuſion of the moſt experienc'd Cavaliers in that exerciſe, he is not very unskilful in his Arms, and for his Dancing, certainly your Highneſs can better judge of that than I: it is true he has but little inclination to the French and Latine Tongues, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs he underſtands the one, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154259:12"/>begins to ſpeak the other; but if your Highneſs will permit me to ſpeak my opinion, I muſt tell you if that <hi>Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle Margaret</hi> were made tutour to the Prince, or were the onely thing he were to ſtudy, he would without all queſtion profit much better then he does. For he ſpends more time in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king love to this Lady, then he allows to his Leſſons: whil'ſt the Ducheſs and the Marquis were in this diſcourſe, the young Duke came into the walk, and the Ducheſs immediately askt him, if it were true that the Marquis ſaid; to which he ſuddenly made anſwer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examining what it was, that it was a thing impoſſible for him to anſwer a demand upon the ſudden of a thing he was ignorant of; the Ducheſs would have preſſed him further, but that minute ſhe receiv'd Letters of great concern from <hi>Venice</hi> which ſhe read, and communicated them to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis as ſhe was wont to do all Papers of publick buſineſs. In the mean time the young Dukes affection for Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle <hi>Margaret</hi> increaſed every day, and grew faſter then he; he ador'd and reſpected her, and he did not ſeem to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154259:13"/>live when he was abſent from her, though but a moment, every one knows there is no Lady in the Court ſo Fair, nor ſo cruel, whom intereſt and ambition does not ſoften, to gain the love of their Prince, nay, the very men of Quality, the moſt conſiderable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Courtiers often ſhut their eyes and ſerve their Prince, neer thoſe of their own Relations; certainly there never was a Prince ſo paſſionately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd by the Ladies as this Duke <hi>Charles;</hi> he was often treated by many great men, to no other end but to ſhew him their wives, or their Daughters, but to their great diſappointment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this Prince lookt onely modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon them, his love to Madamoiſelle <hi>Margaret</hi> made him neglect all others, looking upon none but her with tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and love, and often proteſted he would not change her for all the Faireſt Ladies in the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>And now this young Duke is ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd to his eighteenth year of age, I will call him no longer the little Duke. This Duke then went often into the Chamber of Madamoiſelle <hi>Margarets</hi> mother, where he was always flatter'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154259:13"/>and carreſs'd, nay, the mother her ſelf ſhut him up ſometimes with her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and left them alone upon the bed playing together, carrying the Key away in her Pocket. One day the Duke going to walk, perhaps with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, in the Palace Garden, he met the mother and her daughter walking alone in the wood, the Duke no ſooner approached them then he cryed, Mada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle have a care in coming ſo often into this wood you are not raviſht. The mother (who was the craftieſt woman in the world) anſwer'd him preſently, So ſhe is raviſht by a Prince, there will be no great hurt; but the Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed as quickly, You had better let her give the Favour to a Prince, then ſtay till he force it: It is true, ſaid the mother, but Favours gain'd that way are more ſweet and ſecret. The Prince in the mean time took the young Lady by the hand to walk with him in the wood, whil'ſt the mother return'd to the Palace very well pleas'd to leave her daughter in ſuch good company, who ſtay'd three hours together in that place, none knows what they did: But after they had taken their walk the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154259:14"/>Prince waited upon Madamoiſelle <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> to her mothers chamber, to whom he ſaid, Here, Madam, take your daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which I reſtore you in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition you left her with me. I believe what you ſay, Sir, anſwered ſhe, becauſe you are a Prince.</p>
            <p>From that day Madamoiſelle <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> began to take upon her, and ſhew ſome kind of Empire over the Duke, and the Prince found no inclinations in himſelf to reſiſt her. The Ducheſs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd indifferent, and did not ſeem diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd at their Friendſhip, imagining that the Duke was oblig'd one way or other to divert his youth, and ſhe was the more willing to allow him this Friendſhip with Madamoiſelle <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> becauſe ſhe was well acquainted with her diſpoſition, and believ'd ſhe would not ingage the Duke into any diſorder'd way of life prejudiciable to his Perſon or Fortune, and ſo while all this paſt, ſhe ſhut her eyes, and took no notice at all, and though one day ſhe hid her ſelf to watch their actions, yet ſhe could diſcover nothing between them but teſtimonies of a Friendſhip which reaſon allows of.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:154259:14"/>
            <p>But ſince the Love of theſe two perſons was become the general diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, the Ducheſs conſulted many times very ſeriouſly with the Marquis <hi>Arigone,</hi> who very farre from approving this too violent inclination, as many others did, who were well enough pleas'd to let the Duke freely purſue his inclinations: He on the contrary, forgot nothing, to let them ſee they ought to have prevented him: the Marqueſs was preſs'd on by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</p>
            <p>In <hi>Mantua</hi> there dwelt a widow that was one of the moſt conſiderable wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of that place, who was mother to one of the moſt fair and agreeable young Ladys of all that State. This woman who was not very rich in world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goods, ſuiting her ſelf to her fortune, liv'd onely in the quality of a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, and not like a great Lady; The Marquis, who had a paſſionate kindneſs for her, let no occaſion paſs of diverting his melancholly hours at her houſe, and as ſhe was not very cruel to him, ſhe granted him willingly thoſe Favours that Love demands, without expecting intereſt, imagining that the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154259:15"/>Marqueſs, who was naturally very grateful, would not fail, for the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſake, who granted him all things, to ſerve the Daughter to his Highneſs the Duke; and this opportunity pleas'd the Marqueſs very well, of ſhewing himſelf grateful to the kind Widow, in procuring the Love of the Duke for her Daughter, and alſo of teſtifying his Affection to his Prince, in bringing to him one of the moſt Accompliſh'd young Women amongſt his Subjects; but, ſince he fear'd it a thing impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do, ſo long as this paſsion of the Dukes to the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> continued; he tryed all wayes to ſtifle it, but unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably; becauſe the Duke was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible for all other Women, as well Maids as Wives, that neither the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome nor ugly work'd any effect upon him; for he us'd them both ſo indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently, they had no reaſon to be jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of one another: The Lady <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> was the only Favourite, and the moſt lov'd; and what beauty ſoever hapned to be in the Dukes preſence, he had eyes for none but ſhe.</p>
            <p>One day the Marqueſs imagining that it was impoſſible for the Duke to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154259:15"/>ſee that fine young Lady of his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and not fall in love with her, carryed him to her Mothers houſe, who had invited him to that purpoſe; and had ſpar'd for no Coſt, nor Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to ſet off the Beauty of her Daughter, but all was to no purpoſe: and though the Marqueſs and the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left this young Lady and the Duke alone two houres together in a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the Duke ſate by her, as if ſhe had not been there, without ſpeaking one obliging word to her: The inſenſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Duke was as a Dagger to the heart of this young Lady; and, in truth, What is more vexatious to a Woman, then to ſee, that all the arts ſhe has us'd to gain a heart ſignifie ſo little in the end. The Marquiſs quickly perceiv'd, that the Duke was not very well pleas'd in the place where he had brought him; therefore in returning home to the Palace, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to praiſe her extreamly; the Duke, although he ſeemed to take no notice, and yet nevertheleſs forc't by the Marqueſs to ſpeak of that Ladies Beauty he came from, ſaid to the Marqueſs, My Lord, This Lady is faire
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154259:16"/>enough for you, who ſees her every day, but not for me, who never ſaw her before, and looks not upon her ſo often as you do: The Marqueſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, Your Highneſs muſt then ſee her often, that you may think her fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than now you do: The Duke an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd ſmiling, If I ſhould ſee her once more, certainly I ſhould think her more ugly then I do now. The poor Marqueſs was mad at this, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when the Duke, whil'ſt they were talking, turn'd about and ſhew'd him the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> who they met in the Street; See there, my Lord Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, ſaid he, there is the faireſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all that are faire.</p>
            <p>Whil'ſt theſe things paſt, the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs growing angry, to ſee her Son ſo far gone in Love with the Lady <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet,</hi> carryed by ſome unknown Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick reaſons, and perhaps at the earneſt Solicitations of the Marqueſs, ſent the Mother and the Daughter away to <hi>Caſal,</hi> yet with all the Civility imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and with a particular Promiſe to Marry her very ſuddenly, as indeed it happen'd ſoon after: The Duke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd no great ſigns publickly of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154259:16"/>for her going away, hiding his trouble, without all doubt, very prudently, to take all ſuſpition from the Court: Till then, it was believ'd by moſt, that nothing but vertue had paſs'd between this Lady and the Duke; but others, that lookt nearer into the buſineſs, and could ſee farther into matters of Love, believ'd the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; not being able to imagine, how Vertue could ſubſiſt with ſo great a Liberty: and that a young Girle, who deſir'd nothing more then the heart of a Prince, could refuſe him any thing. The Duke certainly was not without deſires, nor the young Lady without a good will; the youth of them both, and the great liberty allowed them, gave ſtrange cauſes of ſuſpition: In fine, believe who will, that all their time was ſpent in ſaying their Chape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and their Pater-noſters, for my part I never will.</p>
            <p>Some time before the parture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> the Duke had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y long and private Conferences with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> where there wanted no Tears on b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h ſides at that cruel ſeparation, as a W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Woman obſerv'd; he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154259:17"/>forbear promiſing to Write to her, till he had the opportunity of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to viſit her at <hi>Caſal,</hi> which he gave her his Word ſhould be very ſuddenly: Theſe Proteſtations of the Dukes rais'd her Heart a little, which was ſo ſunk with the Fears and Troubles of a cruel Abſence ſhe was to ſuffer, and gave her courage to ask his Highneſs a word or two under his Hand, every moneth at leaſt; which Favour ſhe demanded of him in theſe Words; If your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs will pleaſe to Write to me once every moneth, it will give me every day a Paradice: The Duke embracing her, ſaid, with all the tenderneſs of a paſſionate heart, go, and believe, that nothing in the World ſhall ever be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to carry me from loving you.</p>
            <p>She was ſcarce arriv'd at <hi>Caſal,</hi> but the Duke writ a Letter to her, as well for his own ſatisfaction, as for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of her he Lov'd, it was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:154259:17"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>MARGARET,</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Heart;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THis is the firſt Letter which I write to you, with one of thoſe Pens that are guided by Love; I addreſs to you, whom I alone adore, as the onely and firſt object of my Love: To tell you how ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible I am of your abſence, you muſt aske this Heart, which thinks more of you, then of it ſelf; I do not ſware it to you; the Words of Princes needs no Oaths to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize them: however, I ſhall give you ſuch proofes, that you your ſelf will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire greater. Let me know the ſucceſs of your Voyage, and the ſtate of your Health ſince you went from hence, and whether you Love him that is wholly your</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CHARLES.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This <hi>Letter</hi> was given in charge to a Poſt that was ſent from Court to the Governour of <hi>Caſal,</hi> with expreſs Order to give it to no other hands but ſhe to whom it was directed: The Joy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154259:18"/>of this young Lady was ſo extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in receiving it, that ſhe read it three or four times over in the preſence of the Man that brought it; and every time with a Face over-joy'd, to that extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſhe ſeem'd to him, ſhe would have eaten it, that ſo her heart might have been the Cabinet to preſerve it. The Mother was not at home when her Daughter was thus entertaining the Poſt, and examining him with great concern of the Dukes health, and chiefly of his Employments; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he did not particularly Viſit ſome Lady or other with great Familiarity: but, in theſe Queſtions to him, ſhe ſeem'd not to underſtand what ſhe did, for a Man of that condition, that ſees the Court but at a diſtance, is not to be askt ſuch Queſtions: But, it is true, ſhe was at that time to be pardon'd, ſince the occaſion of that Letter was enough to put her into extraordinary tranſports for him ſhe Lov'd. The Mother being return'd, gave order for ſomething for the Poſt to eate, whil'ſt in the mean time ſhe read over and over again with her Daughter the Dukes Letter, and conſulted together for the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154259:18"/>Anſwer, which they return'd by the ſame Meſſenger, in theſe words;</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Great PRINCE;</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>To tell your <hi>Highneſs</hi> how much comfort your Letter gave me, is impoſsible for me to expreſs; I could not defend my ſelf from vanity, in reading ſo many proofes of Affection from your <hi>Highneſſes</hi> Goodneſs: if I were not well acquainted with the nature of it, which is indulgent to all thoſe who like me, Courts with a moſt humble Reſpect all opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of obeying your <hi>Highneſſes</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. It will not be hard for you to find amongſt your Subjects a Merit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mine; but, I Queſtion very much if your <hi>Highneſs</hi> can find any more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionate to your Service then I am: I have already Sworn to you all the Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Service can be expected from a Perſon of my Sex. It belongs to your <hi>Highneſs</hi> to Command, and me to Obey; yet my Feares tell me, that you do not ſo often think of Commanding me, as I do of Blindly Obeying you. As for the Account you are Graciouſly pleaſed to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154259:19"/>deſire of my Journey hither, I aſſure your <hi>Highneſs,</hi> it had been very pleaſant and happy for me, if every ſtep I made to <hi>Caſal</hi> had not carryed me from what I left behind at <hi>Mantua,</hi> ſo dear to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e: Your <hi>Highneſs</hi> asks me if I love you; How can you believe it poſsible to be ſo ungrateful, not to love a Prince that loves me. I will ſay nothing more, but that I am and will be, to your <hi>Highneſs,</hi> Great Prince,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>A moſt Humble, and Obedient Servant,</hi> Margaret.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Mantua</hi> had a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, of going three or four times eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry year to <hi>Caſal,</hi> to Viſit that place, ſo conſiderable, for its Scituation, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the Capital City of <hi>Montfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat:</hi> The Duke reſolved for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to make that place his ordinary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence; carryed more by his Love to the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> then for Intereſt of State: And none can expreſs with what repugnance he quitted that Town to go to <hi>Mantua,</hi> when at any time the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154259:19"/>neceſsity of his Affaires called him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; yet he indevour'd to conceal the true reaſon of his ſtay ſo much in that place, by pretending the Ayre was ſo much better; ſaying often, That the Ayre of <hi>Mantua</hi> was an Ayre for <hi>Monks</hi> to dwell in, but that of <hi>Caſal</hi> was an Ayre for the Seat of a Prince: And, in truth, he was very much in the right, when he ſpoke ſo of thoſe two places, ſo contrary to each other; for the Ayre of <hi>Caſal</hi> was extraordinary good, and that of <hi>Mantua</hi> had nothing at all commendable in it: though, 'tis true, the Ayre where Princes reſide purifies admirably. All Affaires the Duke took in hand at <hi>Mantua</hi> proſper'd very ill; but, on the contrary, it ſeem'd that <hi>Caſal</hi> was Fortunate to all his Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes: There was ſcarce a day but the Duke complained of ſome Indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or other whil'ſt he was at <hi>Mantua;</hi> his Head, his Stomach, and I know not how many more Infirmities tormented him, or at leaſt he pretended it: but, when he was at <hi>Caſal,</hi> he never made the leaſt complaint of any thing, whether he had cauſe or not; but, if it hapned, that ſome Fits of an Ague,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154259:20"/>Feaver, or any diſtemper ſeiz'd upon him at <hi>Caſal,</hi> he would lay the fault upon his having ſtaid too long at <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dukes of <hi>Mantua</hi> have a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace near to <hi>Caſal,</hi> call'd the <hi>Margaret,</hi> whether they have alwayes been accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom'd to divert themſelves ſome time of the Summer; and there was a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian in <hi>Mantua,</hi> who, being pretty well acquainted with the temper of the Duke, and the inclination he had for the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> underſtood very well, that all theſe Diſtempers the Duke ſo often complained of at <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua,</hi> had no other cauſe but an Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Feaver; and therefore he fail'd not to adviſe the Duke to viſit often that wholſome Ayre of <hi>Caſal:</hi> And, whil'ſt the other Phyſitians were ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the cauſe of the Dukes diſeaſe, and buſying their heads to find a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, this wiſe happy brother of theirs advis'd the Ayre of <hi>Margaret</hi> as the only place of Cure for his Highneſs, and was well rewarded for his paines by the Duke, whoſe delight at <hi>Caſal</hi> you may eaſily imagine was great, and his health perfect. The ſatisfaction of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154259:20"/>going to <hi>Caſal,</hi> and leaving <hi>Mantua,</hi> was plainly diſcover'd in the different Journeys he made, in going and return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between thoſe two places; by the haſt he made to the one, and the ſlow pace he went towards the other: to <hi>Mantua</hi> he went with a <hi>Tortoyſes</hi> pace, and to <hi>Caſal</hi> he flew as faſt as an <hi>Eagle:</hi> Whenſoever his Important Affaires ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd him to go from <hi>Caſal</hi> to <hi>Mantua,</hi> he Travell'd like a Prince; but, when he was to leave <hi>Mantua,</hi> and go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Caſal,</hi> he went in Poſt. The Paſtimes of the Duke were not very great, nor divertizing to the Court, for his greateſt pleaſure was in viſiting the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> in whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany his moſt delightful houres were ſpent; and it was no great difficulty for a young Prince to entertain himſelf very pleaſantly with a young handſome Woman, inſtructed by an old cunning Mother; who, in her youth, had at one time oblig'd more then four ſeveral <hi>French</hi> Gentlemen, whil'ſt they ſtaid at <hi>Caſal.</hi> The houſe of this Lady was not far from the Caſtle, in one of the faireſt Streets of the Town, in which place the Tennis Court was kept; the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:154259:21"/>Duke, who hated Tennis when he was at <hi>Mantua,</hi> took great delight in it at <hi>Caſal;</hi> perhaps to ſhew his Miſtriſs his addreſs; but, he ſpoyl'd his own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: For, he not being able to take his Eyes from the Window where ſhe was, he hardly ſtroke one Ball of three. It was no ſmall diverſion to the ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to ſee thoſe two Lovers ſpeak with their Eyes and Hands, and uſe a thouſand other pleaſant Geſtures, in that place, where there was conſtantly more perſons aſſembled to obſerve them, then to ſee the good play of thoſe that were at Tennis: In the mean time jealouſie ſeiz'd furiouſly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the Ladies in that place; but, amongſt them all, it chiefly laid hold of a young Woman whoſe name was <hi>Nata,</hi> Grandchild to the Preſident; ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt dyed with envy at the Dukes Courtſhip to the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving her ſelf much handſomer than her Couſin the Lady <hi>Margaret;</hi> and had great deſires (at leaſt) to ſhare with her in the Dukes Affection: and her Grief increaſed the more from the vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation ſhe had, to ſee, that all her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Ornaments had not power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154259:21"/>to draw one kind look from his Highneſs, for whom ſhe had dreſt her ſelf to no purpoſe. The Duke never went to Play, but by his dearly Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Margarets</hi> command, his Linnen was alwayes brought to her Houſe; he ſcarce toucht the Ball three times, but away he muſt go to ſhift himſelf in her Chamber, leaving the reſt of the Players at Tennis, ſometimes three houres, to wait till he came down to make an end, which he ſometimes commanded them to do. A <hi>French</hi> Gentleman hapning to be in the Tennis Court one day, was by chance on the Dukes ſide, who was gone up, as his Cuſtom was, to the Lady <hi>Margaret;</hi> this <hi>Frenchman,</hi> impatient (as thoſe of his Nation commonly are) at the Dukes giving ſo long a time to rub himſelf, fell into a paſſion, and ſaid publickly to one of his Camerades; If the Duke of <hi>Mantua</hi> muſt (as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported) have the Command of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Army for the King of <hi>Spain, Lombardy</hi> will quickly be ours; for he takes up more time in changing his Shirt, then the <hi>French</hi> do in taking a Town.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:154259:22"/>
            <p>There was no body but plainly ſaw this ſo often changing of Linnen was rather a pretence of the Dukes, than neceſſity; nothing moving him to run up to her Chamber, but ſome Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous fancy, which the fight of her at the Window awaken'd in him; and there was great reaſon to believe it, for ſhe never ſtirr'd out of the Balcony as long as the Prince was in the Tennis Court; but, immediately vaniſh'd when he went out to go to her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; and, aſſoon as he was got into the Street, to return to his Play, ſhe appear'd in the Balcony again: which, diſcover'd eaſily, that he ſought no pleaſure, but that, of being near his Goddeſs; and ſhe glory'd in nothing more, then to let the People ſee, ſhe had been giving him his Shirt.</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Mother of this young Lady, and alſo the Duke, begun ſeriouſly to think, of finding out a Match for this beloved <hi>Margaret,</hi> who wanted no pretenders, her power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great with the Duke; who, in this deſign, to Marry her, intended not ſo to rid himſelf of her, whom he lov'd paſſionately: Nor did the old
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:154259:22"/>Mother reſolve ſo to loſe her; but, they took this way, to diſguiſe thoſe ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful effects, which uſually follow theſe kind of diſhoneſt Paſſions, as it ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily happens in <hi>Italy,</hi> where the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band often ſerves for a Cover: For, an unmarryed Woman, though ſhe is Courted by a Prince, is lookt upon in that Country as infamous, if ſhe enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him; But on the contrary, let a Marryed Woman be never ſo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſhe is nevertheleſs very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd amongſt all Ladies of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt quallity.</p>
            <p>The Family of this Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> had been ſo blaſted by the abominable carriage of her Mother with the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> her eldeſt Siſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er particularly, whoſe name was the Counteſs <hi>Louize,</hi> lately a Widow, had been notorious, and had liv'd the life of a common Curtizan, taking Mony of any body; living that kind of life, which is ſo much practiſed amongſt thoſe Women, ſo well known by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellors; ſhe fell in love with a <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> who came off better cheap, and almoſt for a ſimple Grand Mercy; he being, as one may ſay, more Courted
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154259:23"/>by that young Widow, then he car'd for, which made her fall into ſtrange diſorders, when he was forc'd to return into <hi>France</hi> with the <hi>French</hi> Army, in which he was an Officer, and left that poor diſconſolate Widow to re-take that habit of Mourning ſhe had ſo late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quitted; and, it is believ'd, ſhe had remain'd unconſolable, if the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> place had not been kindly taken up by a young Earle in <hi>Caſal;</hi> but, what was moſt remarkable, was this Counteſſes flattering her ſelf with the hopes of Marrying this young Earle, by the Credit her Siſter had with the Duke, and his Authority; ſhe gave him all the Liberties imaginable, and they liv'd together like Man and Wife, with ſo publick a Scandal, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop intended to Excommunicate them, but was ſoon prevented from that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for, the young Earle at laſt cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Embraces of that Lady, and weary of her Addreſſes, began to leave her off by little and little; which, the Counteſs perceiving, addreſs'd her ſelf to her Siſter, deſiring her to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Duke, to Command the Earle to Marry her; which, when the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:154259:23"/>Duke went about to do, the young Earle briskly anſwered; Sir, The Earles of <hi>Caſal</hi> do not uſe to Marry Whores: Thus this poor abus'd Counteſs ſought her ſatisfaction in her patience, and try'd no more that vain attempt, of Marrying the Earle by the Dukes Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Juſtice, as her Siſter incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged her to hope; for the Earle Swore, he would rather a thouſand times die a Man of Spirit, then live a baſe Cuckold: So the Counteſs ſeeing Force would do her no good, employ'd Mildneſs and Careſſes to gain him; but the Earle being well acquainted with the Crafts of Women, us'd his oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, took ſome times his pleaſure, and derided Matrimony: Nevertheleſs the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> had pretenders good ſtore, who were drawn more by their Ambition, becauſe of the Empire ſhe had over the Duke, then by any other Motive; whil'ſt ſhe minded nothing more then the enjoying her pleaſures at full liberty, which ſhe could only do by getting a Husband quickly; but a Husband of her own chuſing, fit for the purpoſe; that is to ſay, a good ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man, and one as the <hi>Italian</hi> ſayes,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:154259:24"/>
               <hi>Un gran cog, &amp;c.</hi> — The Mother and Daughter both jump'd in this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; the Mother fearing, that if her Daughter ſhould chance to fall into the hands of ſome Fantaſtick Husband, ſhe might loſe all her authority over her; and they both together fear'd, that his ill humour might be the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ruining her Favour with the Duke, and ſo they ſhould be quite un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, and loſe all their hopes. The Duke alſo was mindful of his own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in that Affair, and conſented not to the Marriage of his Miſtreſs but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe termes; chuſing rather to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs her in that condition ſhe was alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, then loſe her in another. The Dutcheſs, on her ſide, conſidering the Intereſt of State, the conſervation of the Houſe of <hi>Gonzague,</hi> and for the general ſatisfaction of her Subjects, looking upon the Duke as the onely prop of her Family, deſir'd, and ſought nothing more then to ſee this Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> Marryed away; fearing, leaſt the Duke might, loſing himſelf in this extreame ridiculous Love for her, think of Marrying her himſelf: At that time there came to <hi>Caſal</hi> the Earl of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:154259:24"/>
               <hi>Rovera,</hi> a man made for their purpoſe, and made as ſuch a man ſhould be; he he was born at <hi>Savona,</hi> and deſcended from that noble Family of <hi>Rovera,</hi> which has given to the Church thoſe two famous Popes <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Julius</hi> the ſecond. The humour of this Lord was very peaceable and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired, not caring to ſee any body but thoſe of his old acquaintance. In fine, he was a true Ball for theſe Ladies to toſs, and ſuch a one as the Duke, the mother and daughter all deſired; and to ſpeak him in one word, he was of a humour to let them do what they pleas'd, and go were they had a mind to; and though he was not a man of great Learning, yet he was for all that, a man of very good ſenſe, and his wit was capable of ſerving him better than his Language.</p>
            <p>The deſign of this Earl had been to paſs his Life in a ſingle condition, if the ſollicitations of the Duke and the Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> (who was reſolv'd not to let ſlip this occaſion) had not alter'd his reſolutions, and from the firſt day he made her a viſit, put him into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of not being able to live one
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:154259:25"/>day without ſeeing her: Whil'ſt they were treating of this marriage, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Margaret,</hi> to try whether the Earl were of a jealous humour, pretended one day (as he ſat muſing by himſelf in her Chamber) that the Duke had ſent for her to play at Cards with him, ſo that ſhe ſhould be oblig'd to ſtay there with her mother till the next day; and to perſwade the Earl abſolutely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Duke loved her paſſionately, She told him, That the Duke loving her as he did, ſhe could do no leſs than to ſatisfie him in all things that depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon her: but the Earl not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding her, or at leaſt, pretending not to know her meaning, onely anſwer'd, She would do very well to ſerve his Highneſs, and ſo went away.</p>
            <p>One of the neareſt kindred to the Earl, hearing of this intended marriage, went to him with deſign to ſpeak free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to him concerning it as a Friend, and told him, he ought to think more than once upon what he was going to do, and that he ſhould ſeriouſly conſider, (before he proceeded any further) upon the love between the Duke and the Lady <hi>Margaret;</hi> but the Earl anſwer'd,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:154259:25"/>Matrimony will break that Friendſhip. That ſame Friend of his indeavour'd to prove the contrary to him by a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred reaſons, but could get no other anſwer from him (after he had thankt him kindly for his advice) but this, The horns that are grafted by a Prince do not ſit heavy upon the head. Two days after another of his Friends told him openly, that for his part he would not marry that young Lady for any thing in the world, becauſe that as long as the Duke lived, he could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain from being jealous, and ſhould aſſuredly die a Cuckold. This ſecond advice amaz'd the Earl a little, yet he ſaid onely that he believed nothing of all theſe reports. In the mean time this renewed advice wrought ſuch an effect, that he went not to ſee his Miſtreſs in two days, but love being ſtronger, he could not refrain from viſiting her again, ſo great was his deſire to marry her and make her his dear half.</p>
            <p>The Duke ſeem'd to take no notice of all theſe Paſſages, (though they made a noiſe great enough,) but waited till the Earl ſpoke to himſelf about it, which he at laſt did, at the ſolicitation
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:154259:26"/>of the mother, who let him know that her houſe had been always protected by his Highneſs, and her daughter in particular, to whom the Duke had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways expreſſed much friendſhip, and ſhe could do nothing without his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs conſent and approbation. The Earl anſwer'd her preſently, That all Gentlemen were as much oblig'd to this duty, and that they were not wont to marry without they were certain of the Princes aſſent, and therefore it was his duty to do the ſame thing; after this reply he parted from her to go to the Duke, that old Lady having promis'd him to do the like in behalf of her daughter. The Earl had ſcarce began his complement to the Duke concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his marriage with the Lady <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> when the Duke interrupted him to ſpeak to him advantageouſly of her Family and her Perſon, aſſuring the Earl of his affection and protection in all things; and to let him ſee how much he approv'd of this marriage, he told him with a great demonſtration of love, that he was certain that one or both could not but be happy, ſince it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to find a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:154259:26"/>woman nor more worthy of ſuch a husband, nor for her to find a husband more worthy of ſuch a wife. The Earl after he had paid his reſpects and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd thanks to the Duke, ſaid to him, I marry the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> becauſe ſhe is protected by your Highneſs. To which the Duke preſently replyed, laughing, We will love the Lady <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet,</hi> and we will love her until death, having been brought up together from the beginnings of our life. The Duke after he had diſcours'd a long time with the Earl concerning the particularities of this wedding, took him by the hand, and ſaid to him, Go, my Lord, you will gather a Flower, worthy of ſuch a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vera.</hi> My Tree (ſaid the Earl) wants a Flower which comes from the hands of your Highneſs. This marriage then concluded to the ſatisfaction of the intereſted parties, they received all the Complements, and made their Balls and Feaſts <hi>a la mode de France,</hi> which had been maſters of <hi>Caſal,</hi> more then fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years, and had ſo well eſtabliſh'd the French Liberty in that Town to the delight of the inhabitants, that they reſolv'd to keep it for ever; and it is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:154259:27"/>certain, that if they were to change their maſter, they would accept of no other but the moſt Chriſtian King; ſo well do they remain ſatisfied with the French Nation, which is a thing extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary in <hi>Italy,</hi> where they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſo much hated, though the <hi>Italians</hi> can give no reaſon for their averſion to thoſe People: For it is moſt certain, that in thoſe Places of <hi>Italy</hi> where any of the French inhabit, they bring in one moneth more profit to that place, than the <hi>Spaniards</hi> afford them in ten year. The Duke, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though invited to this wedding, could not reſolve upon any conſideration, to ſee his Lady <hi>Margaret</hi> given away, to whom he writ this Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Heart,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IF I thought that thy Marriage would deprive me of thoſe Priviledges I have hitherto injoyed with thee, for certain I ſhould rejoyce very little at it, but I do rejoyce, becauſe I aſſure my ſelf thou marrieſt with a reſolution to give thy Husband but the leavings of our love:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:154259:27"/>heretofore we have been forc'd to do all things ſecretly to hide them from all the world; but from this day we ſhall find it more eaſie to conceal our actions from onely one man; give him the appearances, but do thou be ſure to keep thy heart for me, and remember that I am wholly thine,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Charles.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Duke let ſlip no occaſion of being preſent at all the Balls that were preſented to the Bride in ſeveral places; and one day he was in a dreſs that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guized him ſo much, that he had never been diſcovered but by his great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with the Bride. The Duke having taken notice of a Diamond upon the Bridegrooms finger in the faſhion of a Heart, which himſelf had given his Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> when ſhe was a maid, and was eſteemed worth a thouſand Crowns, was ſo extreamly angry to ſee the Earl wear it, that he reſolv'd to go away from <hi>Caſal</hi> without ſpeaking to her, but ſhe having ſmoakt him, us'd all her endeavour to appeaſe him, and bring him back again, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:154259:28"/>he was in a miſtake, to believe ſhe had given that Ring to her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, which ſhe eſteem'd ſo much for his Highneſs ſake, as the pledge of his affection, that it was more dear to her than any thing in the world. The Duke ſoftned by her tears, dried them up, not with a handkercher, but with his kiſſes, and after that ſtaid in her Chamber with her for ſome hours that day.</p>
            <p>The wedding was kept with ſo great pomp and magnificence, that there wanted nothing but the publick pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Duke, who though he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd to appear there in perſon, yet to ſhew how much he honour'd them, he ſent the Bride a Medal of gold, in which was a Daizy, (which ſignifies <hi>Margaret</hi>) ſet round with twelve Diamonds, and two Chains of great value, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with this note,</p>
            <q>I adviſe thee to be cautious in the captivating thy ſelf, and conſider, if thou art a priſoner to two perſons, it will not be eaſie to cheat both thy keepers.</q>
            <p>The love of the Duke to the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:154259:28"/>Counteſs ſeem'd after this wedding to grow by little and little ſomething cool, but it was but a feigned coldneſs: For he often found his opportunities of entertaining her in private during his ſtay at <hi>Caſal.</hi> The Earl us'd all the art he was capable of to ſurprize his wife in her private conferences with the Duke, but in vain; ſo that at laſt he began to believe ſhe had been ſlander'd, and ſo reſted in peace, giving her all kind of Liberty; who had wit enough to make the right uſe of it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented the Husband in publick, and the Gallant in private; but ſince now the Time and Neceſſity of the State ſeem'd to demand a Succeſſour to the Duke, ſo to conſerve that rich Patrimony ſtill in the ſame Houſe where it had long continued, and there being no other branch left of the houſe of <hi>Gonzague</hi> but himſelf; The whole State begun now to think in good earneſt of marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to ſome Princeſs worthy of ſo great a Prince, many matches were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, but heaven, that ordinarily takes care of making marriages, ordain'd the Archducheſs <hi>Iſabella Clare,</hi> a Princeſs worthy of a Crown, to be this Dukes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:154259:29"/>wife, and ſhould by her Life and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience adde a new luſtre to the houſe of <hi>Gonzague;</hi> ſome other woman perhaps would have brought the ſame diſorder into that houſe (and it may be a worſe) than that which the houſe of <hi>Lorraine</hi> experimented in the love which the Duke <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorraine</hi> expreſs'd for the Counteſs of <hi>Cantecroy,</hi> to the prejudice of that affection which he owed to his wife <hi>Nicola.</hi> The Ducheſs, who notwithſtanding all the indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency which ſhe ſaw in her husband to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her, ſhe expreſs'd not the leaſt jealouſie of the Counteſs, and although ſhe ſaw in a little time her husband ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely eſtranged from her, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd altogether in the love of that woman, yet ſhe look'd no leſs kindly upon the Duke her husband, even whil'ſt the Counteſs endeavoured to keep him from her by all the wayes poſſible, having writ this Letter to him, notwithſtanding ſhe knew his Marriage with the Ducheſs was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:154259:29"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Great Prince,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am not ignorant that the marriage of your Highneſs with the Archducheſs <hi>Iſabella Clare,</hi> will bring an increaſe to your Family, a glory to your State, and a comfort to your ſervants, but as faſt as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he joy of poſſeſsing ſo great a Prince does grow in the heart of the Archducheſs, that of my heart will diminiſh in the loſs I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o ſuffer, of a heart that was alwayes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bject of my love, and all my deſires: I hope your Highneſs will pardon me for writing to you in this manner, but in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ondition I am in of looſing what I adore, I can be no longer any thing elſe but an extravagant without conduct or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaſon; but if your Highneſs has been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leaſed to honour me hitherto by loving me as a Friend; I deſire you will at leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontinue your grace and favour to me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n loving, for the time to come, as your moſt humble ſervant</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Margaret.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:154259:30"/>
            <p>The Duke, who lov'd the Counteſs above his own reputation, after he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> read her Letter two or three time over, ſighing, in the preſence of a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of hers who brought it to him tore it, after he had anſwer'd it, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much tenderneſs in theſe words,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Counteſs,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ALl Princes are accuſtomed to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry themſelves more by reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> State then Love; ſo they love the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> wives more by reaſon of State than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> affection. If the intereſt of my houſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not oblige me to marry, nothing ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> hinder me from being alwayes thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> whoſe I ſhall be, in deſpight of all tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> that would oppoſe it; and ſince th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> haſt deceiv'd thy husband to content m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> why cannot I deceive my wife for thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction? trouble thy ſelf for nothing and love thy</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Charles</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:154259:30"/>
            <p>Although the furious warres in the year 1629. had very much exhauſted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he treaſure of that State, yet the Ducheſs in this time of the marrying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f her ſon ſpar'd for no coſt, to render <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t very ſplendid and magnificent; all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Ladies of Honour that had liv'd in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat Court were invited to make the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntry of the new Princeſs into <hi>Mantua</hi> more glorious. There was none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>epted in that invitation but the Counteſs, who the Ducheſs would not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nvite to that Ceremony, for ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons, which, mortification to the Counteſs ſhe ſoon after complain'd of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Duke, and her reſentment was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eightned by her being, as it were, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aniſh'd from the Court in a time when the Earl her husband had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eiv'd one of the chiefeſt Imployments or the Ceremony of that Entry; of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich place he very well acquitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>imſelf to the Contentment of the Duke his maſter: yet notwithſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll this, the Counteſs would go to <hi>Mantua,</hi> and adorn'd her ſelf with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he gallantries that fine Ladies take at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe times to ſet themſelves off at Court, whither ſhe went to ſee the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:154259:31"/>new Ducheſs, where at laſt the Ducheſs mother to the Duke, gave her leave to ſtay to take part in the divertizement of the Balls, which were given the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> for many dayes together, The fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> great Ball paſs'd without the Duke ſeeming to take any notice of his Lady <hi>Margaret;</hi> and although there w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> more of Prudence than coldneſs of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in this carriage of his, yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Counteſs could hardly refrain from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing thoſe ſignes of anger an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> jealouſie which ſeiz'd upon her heart imagining that the Duke ſatisfied wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the beauty and carreſſes of his Bride began to neglect her charmes, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had ſo long captivated him; ſhe omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no opportunity of ſpeaking to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Duke, who underſtood her, and ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> avoided talking with her, though h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> did not forget to cauſe her to be taken out to dance as well as the other Ladie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Quality, to whom Princes alwaye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> apply themſelves to do them chief ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour at thoſe times. But this politie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſſimulation of the Dukes cold car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to the Counteſs continued but a little while: for before ſhe return'd, to <hi>Caſal</hi> with her husband, his Highneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:154259:31"/>would ſee her, and diſcours'd with her, above an hour in private. I know not in what place they met, but the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Arrigone</hi> paſſing by the place where the Duke and ſhe were talking, and perceiving them together, Your Highneſs (ſaid he) goes back to the <hi>Sicut erat,</hi> before you begin the Pſalm.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs went away very well ſatisfied, after this conference with the Duke, which made it believ'd that his Highneſs confirm'd the proteſtations of his conſtancy to her; but it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for her husband to diſcover the reaſon of that great joy which was in her face at their return to <hi>Caſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe beginnings of the Dukes Marriage, though they paſt thus cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet it was not to be imagin'd that it would continue ſo long; although it is true, that the Thoughts and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of Princes diſpenſes them in ſome ſort from the ordinary practifers of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour People: and, moſt People ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, the Prince has perform'd his duty well enough, if he has got his Wife with Child; nevertheleſs, this Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> whether it were through the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:154259:32"/>tenderneſs of his Age, having ſcarce yet arrived to his one and twentieth year; or through ſome other reaſon, he ceaſed not for three moneths toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Careſs the Dutcheſs his Wife with all ſort of kindneſs; not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his familiar Friends, but alſo in the preſence of the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> themſelves, which was a great contentment to the Dutcheſs his Mother: but 3 Moneths after that, ſome buſineſs at <hi>Montferrat,</hi> or, as it is conjectur'd, the Love to the Counteſs, who deſir'd him impatiently, or as ſome perſwaded themſelves, to leave the Dutcheſs at repoſe, obliged the Duke to go to <hi>Caſal;</hi> This Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age a little alter'd the Dukes Affection to the Dutcheſs his Wife, if one may give the name of Affection to a Love ſo newly planted, whoſe Rootes were yet but ſmall and tender; the ſight of the Counteſs made him forget his Wife: and, it was obſerv'd, he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver taken ſo great a delight in Careſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Dutcheſs, as he took onely in ſpeaking with the Counteſs: but, becauſe the preſence of the Husband was an Obſtacle to their pleaſures, he round out a way by a pretence of buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:154259:32"/>to ſend him to <hi>Mantua:</hi> The Earle, who had from the firſt night of the Dukes arriving at <hi>Caſal,</hi> taken bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter notice of ſome paſſages he was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to diſcover, began then to believe, what till then he had but ſuſpected; nevertheleſs he muſt go by his Prince's Command, without ſhewing any repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for that journey: but, at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, he receiv'd an account of all had paſſed from a waiting Maid, to whom he had made great promiſes of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, with Oaths to perform them, to be a faithful Spy for him, of what paſs'd between the Duke, and his Wife, in his abſence; ſhe promis'd the Earle, to give him an exact Account; but, it was not very difficult for her (the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs not miſtruſting her) to find out the moſt private paſſages for this intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence. The Earle had fooliſhly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that all the Dukes Love had no other Concluſion but Playing at Cards, and perhaps ſome little <hi>French</hi> Freedomes with his Wife; imagining, that her Brothers and Kindred, that were intereſted in the ſame reputation, would have prevented any further ill, but he deceiv'd, himſelf; For, they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:154259:33"/>were of the opinion he himſelf had at firſt declar'd, (that the Hornes Graft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Prince did not ſit uneaſily upon the Head) and were ſo far from watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Actions of the Duke, and their Kinſwoman, to prevent the ſhame of their Houſe, that they were very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious to bring them together, and ſerving the Dukes Loves with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable care and diligence; and the chiefe amongſt them in this imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was he, whom the Duke had lately made Maſter of the Artillery at <hi>Caſal;</hi> it was he that convey'd by night his Siſter into the Dukes Chamber, and moſt commonly kept the Door, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Male that was to carry back his Siſter to her own Lodging, when ſhe had pleaſur'd the Duke: In truth this Amour grew very ſtrong in this laſt Journey; the one began to hate her Husband, to ſatisfie her Gallant; the other, to deſpiſe his Wife, to give himſelf intirely to his Friend; and this was plainly perceiv'd by what happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after the Dukes return to <hi>Mantua;</hi> where he diſcover'd (to the great aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of all the World) that he was Cloyed of his Wife: No body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:154259:33"/>able to imagine, how a young Prince could poſſibly be weary ſo ſoon of a young Princeſs, who alſo was new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prov'd with Child, to the great Joy of the whole Court; whil'ſt in the mean time that chaſt Dove knew not what to think of a Husband ſo young who expreſt ſo little Love to her; and nevertheleſs, although her Grief at it was great, yet her Prudence was greater; ſo that ſhe pretended not to ſee that which ſhe but too much diſcover'd: The Earle, which the Duke had taken order to ſend away to <hi>Mantua,</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not to ſtir from thence till his Highneſs return'd, which he obey'd; and the Duke was no ſooner arrived in the Town, but he ſent him back to his own Houſe, where his Curioſity coſt him dear, and gave him no ſmall Mortification; the Servant he had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd to watch, having given him the whole Relation of all had paſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Duke and his Wife: the ſhame and confuſion of this poor Man is not to be expreſs'd, when he learnt the circumſtances of this Impudent Love countenanc'd by the baſeneſs of is Wives own Brothers; and although
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:154259:34"/>he ſeem'd to take no notice of what he too well knew, nor hearkned to the Diſcourſes of his Friends upon that Chapter; yet, he could not imagine, that the Crimes of his Wife, and his own misfortune was ſo publick: his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly grew to that height, that he ſaw not any body that Saluted him in the Streets; and he fancyed every mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute, that People were making Hornes at him behind his back: The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, who had a good Noſe, ſmelt out the reaſon of the Change in her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands Humour, and redoubled her Careſſes to him; fearing, leaſt this jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie which he appear'd ſo inſenſible of before his Marriage, might produce ſome unhappy effect; for, it is certain, that had ſhe known him to be of a jealous humour, ſhe would never have Marryed him.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, as the Earle and his Counteſs walked one evening after Supper upon the Town Walls, the Earl ask'd his Wife, Did his Highneſs waite upon you often? As he was wont, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd ſhe; (ſeeing to what end he ſpoke it:) And, What did you do together, ſaid the Earle? to which, ſhe anſwer'd,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:154259:34"/>The ſame that you did with the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> at <hi>Mantua.</hi> Thus they both rallyed one another. The Husband perceiving what it was to have ſuch a Wife, and the wife lamented the trouble of having ſuch a Husband: yet nevertheleſs the Earles jealouſies had ſome intermiſſions, his Melancholly often giving place to his Joy; ſo that his Wife, and Brothers in-Law felt ſome time the effects of the one, and then of the other. Whil'ſt theſe things paſs'd in the Year 1652, the Dutcheſs was brought to bed of a Son, which is now the onely Prop of the Houſe of <hi>Gonzague;</hi> the Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Mother; the Glory and Hope of the State, to which he gives great hopes, promiſing very much, ſhewing himſelf a great and brave Prince, and expreſſing averſion for an idle lazy life; and, on the contrary, a great incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation for all the exerciſes of Warr: It is believed, that ſince the Birth of that young Prince, the Duke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd not with the Dutcheſs as his Wife; the reaſon of this opinion is his aſſiduous love to the Counteſs, as alſo becauſe the Dutcheſs has not been with Child from that time.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:154259:35"/>
            <p>This indifference of the Duke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Dutcheſs was alſo imputed to two other cauſes; the firſt, to her Natural coldneſs; the other, to I know not what ſtrange deviſe of the Counteſs: the laſt ſcarce is doubted of; for, as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port has ſaid, this Woman fearing to loſe the Dukes Friendſhip after his Marriage, and ſeeking to injoy alone a good, without which ſhe deſpis'd all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; reſolv'd to tempt all wayes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that, which ſhe thought an obſtacle to her deſign; to that end, having told her thoughts to one of her Siſters, ſhe, by her meanes, became acquainted with it certain Magician, who dwelt at St. <hi>Sauveur,</hi> near to <hi>Caſal;</hi> the Counteſs went to him, and obtain'd ſome words from him; That he bid her be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident ſhe ſhould enjoy the Dukes Friendſhip alone: but, becauſe this Sorcerer was of an intelligence with a certain Religious Dominican, that Lady gain'd him by his meanes; ſhe rewarding him, by not refuſing him the ſatisfaction he requir'd of her: ſo, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that this Charme ſucceeded ſo well by the help of this Reverend Father, that by their Diabolical Inventions, the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:154259:35"/>Duke had that knot tyed, uſually ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to Marriage: Others have believ'd that this was a falſe report, and that this Witchcraft took no effect, but that the Duke made it a pretext to avoid the Dutcheſs, whom he lov'd not; and devote himſelf to the Counteſs, whom he ador'd, in which there is no likelihood: For, let any body imagine how it can be poſſible for a young Prince to live in the company of his Wife without touching her, if there had not been ſome reaſon diabolical, or ſupernatural to hinder him: ſo, that it muſt certainly be believ'd, that the Counteſs did bewitch the Duke.</p>
            <p>The old Dutcheſs, troubled at the Dukes infirmity, told him he ſhould make uſe of ſome ſpiritual or natural remedies to cure him, but (what was very ſtrange) he laught at her advice, which made people believe that it was done by his own conſent.</p>
            <p>It has been ſaid that that natural coldneſs of the young Ducheſs, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to the Conſtitution (ſo contrary) of the Counteſs, contributed very much for the ſmall affection he had for her: but how could the Ducheſs leave
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:154259:36"/>off that purity ſo rare and commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which ſhe had alwayes made the ornament of her life, to comply with the Dukes deſires, and which he found in another? There is no doubt but that ſhe lov'd as much as any other woman could do, but with a ſincere, true and real love, for to ſay truth, ſhe was not in the number of thoſe that onely made a ſhew of love, but ſhe lov'd her husband from the bottom of her heart; ſo that all her affection was within, having not thoſe little fooliſh fondneſſes which ſome other wives ſtudy with ſo much affectation to ſhew their loves: In a word, her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection was truly great, though ſhe did not make ſhew of it; but to clear all this, I think it to ſome purpoſe to ſay ſomething by the way, to diſcover what the Dukes inclinations were na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, and alſo of that of the Counteſs <hi>Margaret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All men naturally take great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Careſſes they receive; it is certain that the Duke was more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to that ſatisfaction than any man; ſo that it may almoſt be ſaid, that weakneſs was a fault of nature in him
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:154259:36"/>who ſo deſired to be courted by the women, without which, it is thought, the Duke would have been inſenſible for them; they ſay that this inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Dukes was caus'd by the Converſation of the Ladies of the Court, amongſt whom he was brought up, and ſpent moſt of his youth, having alwayes been careſs'd by one or other of thoſe Ladies that waited on his Mother, who lov'd nothing more than to ſee the women make much of him, and to be under the conduct of that ſex, and particularly the Lady <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret,</hi> who had ſo us'd him to her car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes, that he could not think of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſing his wife, if he were hot prepar'd by hers, which is a thing that ſeldom happens, but what the one could not do, the other was perfect in, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercis'd her art ſo to the humour of the Duke, that he could not defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from her Charms, though he had a mind to it, alſo the Counteſs was li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral enough of her Courtſhips to him, mov'd rather by ambition to domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neer and govern the Duke, than by any ſentiment of nature, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd by the little care ſhe took to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:154259:37"/>court her husband at that rate; and certainly the very <hi>Sirenes</hi> and <hi>Circes</hi> were never capable of more intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and flattering carreſſes than ſhe us'd to pleaſe the Duke.</p>
            <p>See here the poiſon of this Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, ſee here the Fall of the Dukes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation; a Princeſs too modeſt and little ſenſible of Carreſſes, and a Prince too deſirous of thoſe kind of Charms; and on the other ſide, a woman expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd in all the crafts of Love, to gain the heart of this Prince, and take it from the Princeſs, and it is ſtedfaſtly believ'd, that if the Princeſs had been of her rivals humour, the Duke would have lov'd her as well as he lov'd the Counteſs, and had been as good a Husband as he was a Lover; and that if the Counteſs had not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the way of treating him in another manner than the Ducheſs did, without doubt he would have had no greater a Complaſance for her; but yet it was better for the Princeſs to be as ſhe was, than to be of the humour of her rival: In the mean time, it is eaſie to be believ'd, that the exceſſive carreſſes which the Counteſs made to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:154259:37"/>that Duke made him not only hate the Ducheſs in the way of Matrimony, but alſo to abhorre Marriage it ſelf for her ſake: for to juſtifie this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he was quite contrary to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of other Princes, who delight in change; for he could indure to ſee no other woman but the Counteſs, and it is certainly reported, that except his wife, he never touch'd any other woman but the Counteſs, who was his ordinary Meal every day, and his Feaſt alſo; however one day he was angry at her for ſomething, he to vex her ſent for a young very pretty woman of the town of <hi>Caſal,</hi> and becauſe in that rencounter there happened a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant paſſage, I think it neceſſary enough to mention it in this place in few words: This young Maid liv'd in a houſe on the back-ſide of the Church of the <hi>Auguſtin</hi> Fathers in a ſtreet great enough, the Duke having often paſs'd that way with the Counteſs, fail'd not to look upon her ſtill being at the door on purpoſe to be ſeen by the Duke; This happened a little after the depart of the Earl in his voyage to <hi>Poland,</hi> the Duke rather
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:154259:38"/>to laugh than for any other deſign, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this young woman, us'd to ſay to the Counteſs, That wench is hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer than thou art; It is true ſaid the Counteſs, (peek'd with jealouſie) but ſhe has fewer charmes, therefore I don't fear that ſhe will deprive me of your love which is apter to be taken with agreeableneſs than beauty; but what pleaſure does your Highneſs take to break my head with jealouſie?</p>
            <p>One night when the Duke was angry at her, or counterfeited himſelf ſo, to vex the Counteſs, to trouble her brains yet more, he ſent word to that young woman by one of the Grooms of his Chamber, (who was the ſame that us'd to wait upon the Counteſs to his Chamber at night in the Caſtle) that he would ſpeak with her, and that he ſhould expect her after Supper. Her mother, who underſtood this myſtery, ſaid to the Meſſenger, The words of his Highneſs cannot but produce great grace to my Daughter, who is wholly at his ſervice.</p>
            <p>The hour come, the Groom of the Chamber went to execute the Orders of his Maſter, and to conduct this
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:154259:38"/>young Maid into his Chamber, (I will not ſay into the bed) but the Counteſs, being inform'd by the ſame man, who was her kinſman and a very good friend of hers, ran preſently to the Palace, where having found that Prey, without taking notice of any thing, ran to the Dukes apartement, and preſented her ſelf to the Duke, to make him change his reſolutions, who being made ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by her carreſſes, he caſt himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her arms, whil'ſt the Groom of the Chamber, too crafty to looſe ſo good an occaſion, conducted the young wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which he had brought, into his own Chamber, where he made her ſtay and lye with him; ſo that ſhe ſaw her ſelf conſtrain'd to receive from the man what ſhe expected from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. In the mean time her mother, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hold on this occaſion, bragg'd every where that her daughter had great Familiarities with the Duke, to whom nevertheleſs ſhe had not ſo much as ſpoke a word. The Duke being with his well-beloved, was in ſome apprehenſions that the Groom of his Chamber might ſurprize them with that young wench he had ſent for, but
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:154259:39"/>he found afterwards that all things were carried very well. The Counteſs of her ſide, reproached the Duke very much for his lightneſs and the injuſtice he did her in going about to change a love which he had experienc'd ſo long, for one that was ſo new, and beſides, which was not worth the trouble. The Duke excus'd himſelf, ſaying, All that was but in jeſt, and to make her jealous, from whom he receiv'd thoſe delights anew, which ordinarily is found in the reconcilements of Lovers. But, ſaid the Counteſs, what did that young Wench do in your Palace. The Duke quickly replyed, That if ſhe were come thither, it was for his <hi>valet de Chambre,</hi> and not for him. Your Highneſs then (ſaid the Counteſs) ſerves the Loves of your <hi>valet de Chambre.</hi> Thus the pleaſures baniſh'd the ſuſpicions, and the peace was concluded without much pain.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the young Ducheſs, too well inform'd of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly life, the Duke led with the Counteſs <hi>Margaret,</hi> could not defend her heart from ſuffering all thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which an honeſt and vertuous wife uſually feels upon ſuch an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:154259:39"/>She made ſome tell the Duke her Husband of it, deſiring him to ſtop the Courſe of that diſorder, which was his ſhame, and the ſcandal of his people: Her Prudence made her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal her grief, and her Vertue oblig'd her to ſtifle thoſe reproaches ſhe might have made to the Dukes infidelity, which would draw upon him the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and ſcorn of other Princes; amongſt whom at that time there was not heard of the like. The Duke could not hear the lawful reproaches of his wife the Ducheſs without being touch'd with the remorſe of his crime; but if he ſet before his eyes the wrong and injury which he did to the goodneſs and fidelity of his wife, he faild not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to repreſent to himſelf how little it was in his power to leave off loving the Counteſs. Thus the mortification which he receiv'd from the reproaches was made to him ſerved to no other end but to put him into a condition of not knowing which ſide to take; he knew his crime, but he could not hate the cauſe; and it was impoſſible for him to baniſh out of his ſoul his love to the Counteſs, to place the Ducheſs
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:154259:40"/>in her room; and although he wanted love for his wife, yet he wanted not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to know his diſorder; ſo that he ſought to ſweeten the juſt reſentments of the Ducheſs by all kind of ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in which he let the world ſee that he was very well skill'd in ſaving (as 'tis ſaid) both the Cabbidge and the kid; people wonder'd how he could ſo well both pleaſe his wife and his Miſtreſs, and how it came to paſs that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Ducheſs remain'd better ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied than did the Counteſs, who effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally receiv'd from his Highneſs all kind of ſatisfaction, who wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that ſhe could deſire from him; but it was to be wiſh'd that the Ducheſs could have alſo the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions that the Counteſs had.</p>
            <p>All that the Duke and the Counteſs did had no other end but to ſeek out wayes to injoy one another more often, which happen'd as they wiſh'd. The one ſtudied to deceive her Husband, and the other his Wife: But to ſpeak truth, the Counteſs found it a harder task to cheat her Husband, than the Duke found in deceiving the Ducheſs his Wife: for this poor unfortunate
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:154259:40"/>Lady perceiving that this was an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable evil and deſperate, by a great Prudence ſhut her eyes almoſt, that ſhe might not ſee the diſorders of her Husband; whil'ſt on the other ſide the Earl watch'd his wife, the more that he ſaw her give her ſelf up to the love of the Duke, to her great diſhonour and loſs of her own reputation, and he had juſt reaſon for doing ſo: for ſince they were not aſham'd to act their worthy affairs almoſt before all the world, notwithſtanding all the diligence of the Earl to watch them; what would they not have done, if he had winkt at their excellent Carriage?</p>
            <p>If theſe two Lovers had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to do all in ſecret, the Earl had not been much diſquieted, nor had he taken what they did into his conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but had rather, would have ſeem'd to have receiv'd ſome ſatiſfaction in the hopes of being well us'd by the Duke, and to have receiv'd ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours from him in the fight of the world: For all his great trouble aroſe from the publick ſcandal, and the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he had conceiv'd, that every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy fancied he complyed with theſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:154259:41"/>amours, and thus it made him ſick at heart, to be counted not onely a baſe man, but an infamous voluntary Cuckold, and publickly to be deſpis'd as ſuch a perſon: He never reflected upon the Nobility of his Houſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended originally from great Princes, who had alwayes liv'd honourably, and had mantain'd themſelves for many years by a very advantageous reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without ever receiving any ſtain; but thoſe reflections made him repent he had married a wife, whoſe carriage ſo much diſhonour'd that illuſtrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of his; and the good fame his Predeceſſours had acquired by their honeſt Lives; his anger kindled a thouſand times in his heart the deſire of revenge, but the fear of ſome thing worſe happening to him, and to looſe not onely his fortune but alſo his life, ſtifled all thoſe thoughts in him. Shall I ſay furthermore, the apprehenſion of a ſad end and an untimely death hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd him often from complaining to his wife of her wicked Carriage of her ſelf; He durſt not, I ſay, correct her in ſecret, or to threaten her, fearing that, ſhe being warn'd by that, might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:154259:41"/>to him a violent death in revenge to his upbraids of her: ſo that he was often forc'd to pretend as if he had not ſeen thoſe paſſages he ſaw too plainly, and to be ignorant of what he knew too well. But in fine, not being able to indure any longer a vexation that grew every moment, preſs'd with grief and ſhame, he reſolv'd to go to <hi>Savona,</hi> to ask Counſel of his Parents, what courſe to take to deliver himſelf from a misfortune which was ſo cruel to him and ſo great? and he had ſcarce acoſted them, when one amongſt them reproach'd him of marrying a wife whether they would or no, who was the daughter of an unchaſt mother, the ſiſter of a whore, and whoſe own honour was ſuſpected then when he would ſo obſtinately reſolve to marry her, and her life ſince has prov'd what ſhe was then. The poor Earl, extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mortified with theſe reproaches, could make no other anſwer, but that he never thought things would come to this paſs; his Parents nevertheleſs not to leave him in this Sea of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion counſell'd him after they had comforted him a little, that he ſhould
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:154259:42"/>try to remove his wife from <hi>Caſal</hi> calmly and with Gentleneſs, to bring her to <hi>Savona,</hi> and there reſolve to ſettle and live out the remainder of his days in his own Country.</p>
            <p>This Earl tryed the way of follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this good Counſel, believing for certain that abſence would cool this love, and that time would make him forget what at the preſent was ſuch a heart-breaking to him, and caus'd him ſo much ſhame; being then return'd to <hi>Caſal,</hi> he begun to try if he could work this miracle upon his wife, but all his indeavours were in vain; he told her his Parents deſir'd her company very paſſionately amongſt them, that the Ladies of that Town deſir'd impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to injoy her company, to render her all the ſervice and reſpect they thought due to her; he alſo prayed her to conſider how advantageous the Promiſes of that Republick were to him of making him a great man, by the conſiderable imployments they would give him, and that ſhe ſhould aſſure her ſelf he would ſpare no coſt to give her all ſort of contentments, and to that end he was reſolv'd to purchaſe a little
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:154259:42"/>but fair Lordſhip hard by the Sea-ſide, where in the Summer-time they would divert themſelves together, by all the agreeable divertiſements ſutable to perſons of their condition. In fine, to conclude in a word, he gave her many other politick and moral reaſons, ſo ſtrong and plauſible, that they would have been powerful enough to have convinc'd any body but her ſelf: but the good Counteſs did nothing but laugh at this diſcourſe, and without flattering him any further, told him plainly, That ſhe was not of an humour to quit her own for a ſtrange purchaſe, the certain for the uncertain, and that which ſhe was really poſſeſt of for a picture and ſhadow, that ſhe had not married her ſelf at <hi>Caſal</hi> with inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to dwell at <hi>Savona,</hi> that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of her marriage had made no mention of this change, and that he could by nothing in the world find a lawful excuſe to make her change her own Country; and if he pleas'd he might deſire to ſee his own Relations at <hi>Savona,</hi> but as for her ſhe would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtay in the Company of her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at <hi>Caſal,</hi> and after all ſhe aſſur'd
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:154259:43"/>him it was loſs of time to dream of that, becauſe ſhe was confident his Highneſs would never conſent to their parture, and yet to depart without his conſent it was blindly to precipitate her ruine, and thus the Earl was, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd to deſiſt from his enterprize, and ſaw himſelf oblig'd to arm himſelf with a new patience. The Counteſs the whileſt judging by theſe words, that he had a deſign to retire her from her Lover; imagining beſides, that her Husband had prepar'd for her at <hi>Savona</hi> ſome of thoſe Morſels which the <hi>Italians</hi> ordinarily give to their wives in the like Caſes, as it often happens in <hi>Italy;</hi> which made her ſeek an opportunity to ſpeak to the Duke, and having eaſily found him, as ſhe wiſh'd, ſhe having the Liberty to go and come to him at all hours, after ſhe had acoſted him and made her curtſie, ſhe told him at length the whole ſtory of her Husbands deſignes, not forgetting his very words in a manner, that ſhew'd how angry ſhe was at her Husband. This reſolution of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly diſpleas'd the Duke, who lookt upon the Earl as very little
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:154259:43"/>politick, and not at all prudent, and thought it very ſtrange that for a fooliſh trifle (for he lookt upon the making a man a Cuckold nothing elſe) he would hazard the loſs of his favour in retiring from his ſervice, he was of opinion that the honours he conferr'd on the Earl was ſatisfaction enough for the honour he took from him, and that he had done him Favour great enough in making him one of the moſt conſiderable of his Court, which he had not done upon any conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world, but for the Love he had for the Counteſs.</p>
            <p>But if the Earl conſulted his Parents at <hi>Savona,</hi> to carry the Counteſs thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of <hi>Caſal,</hi> the Duke and ſhe conſulted at <hi>Caſal</hi> againſt him, and ſought out Pretences to abſent in good earneſt that obſtacle of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights from them: for is was every day a new work, and every time that this Lover came to <hi>Caſal</hi> he was in trouble to invent ſome new pretext to be rid of him, to the end that he might ſupply his place with the Counteſs, and divert themſelves with more Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; But the Duke came ſo often
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:154259:44"/>to <hi>Caſal,</hi> and was ſo often put to his ſhifts to find out new pretexts of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſing the Earl out of the way, that he was now at the bottom of his ſcrowl, and his invention being tyred, he knew not what to do next: theſe Lovers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded many wayes to one another, whereof one was to ſhoot him private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with a Musquet, and pretend after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that the blow came from ſome of his enemies; but the Prince could not hearken to this reſolution, not being willing, after the example of <hi>David,</hi> to add murther to his adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, not being aſſured that he ſhould repent as he did; beſides, the Counteſs her ſelf was not of a nature ever to give her conſent to any actions of cruelty, the leaſt in the world; or any that thus was an offence to the Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Matrimony, notwithſtanding the heat that appear'd in her firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and paſſion againſt her husband. They had already ſent him to <hi>Rome,</hi> twice to <hi>Florence,</hi> as many times to <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> and I know not how many times to <hi>Turin</hi> and <hi>Genes.</hi> The Duke at laſt would ſend him into <hi>France,</hi> in the quality of an Ordinary Embaſſadour,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:154259:44"/>but there were two obſtacles that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred that, The hate and averſion the Earl ever bore to the French Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was one, and indeed his declared averſion to them was ſo unreaſonable, that he was us'd to ſay in all Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies where he came, that if he had the Keyes of Hell but one day, he would with his whole heart ſend all the Frenchmen thither, even to the Devils Palace, becauſe they had cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the City of <hi>Caſal,</hi> and by the introduction of their Liberty had ſo chang'd that Town <hi>en bordeau.</hi> Thus it appear'd not reaſonable to the Duke to ſend ſuch a man to treat with them. In the ſecond place, that which hindred the Earl from being ſent Embaſſadour into the Court of <hi>France,</hi> was, The Fear the Duke had he would cary his wife along with him, (as aſſuredly he had done;) and the Duke refuſing to let her go, would have diſoblig'd him too much, and given cauſe to an apparent ſcandal, and therefore this Propoſition took no effect, and ended juſt where it begun, as unprofitable to their deſign; but the reſolution was certainly taken to diſmiſs the Earl one way or other,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:154259:45"/>if not for ever, yet for a great while; but they endeavour'd to find out ways for their ſatisfaction that would ſuit with the glory of the Husband and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Wife, which they lookt upon chiefly in this deſign. As for the abſenting of her brothers, there was no thought of that; for they were very merry and well contented to ſee their Siſter in the Dukes good graces, and envied one another, who ſhould moſt contribute to the pleaſures of the Duke and their Siſter. The profit they receiv'd was ſo great by it, beſides the conſiderable charges conferr'd upon them for their ſervice in that trade; in truth thoſe Gentlemen might well enough diſſemble their trouble, to ſee their Siſter live ſo diſorder'd a life, and content themſelves more eaſily to be the procurers of horns; ſince that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was not ſo great a diſ-reputation to them as it was to the Earl that was the Husband, who was to endure not onely the publike knowledge of his diſhonour, the injuries and reproaches of all the world, but alſo the pride and ill humour of his wife in his houſe, without daring to take notice of his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:154259:45"/>being ſent away from her, ſo often, whole weeks and moneths, which was inſupportable to him: therefore it muſt not be wonder'd, if the Earl was weary of that life, as well as the Duke was of ſeeking out excuſes to ſend him abroad, to injoy his wife with more Liberty, who at laſt thought of a way very fit for his deſign.</p>
            <p>There is in the Kingdom 'of <hi>Poland</hi> a Marqueſs of <hi>Gonzague,</hi> very much eſteem'd by all the people in that Countrey, who although they are not of the ſame line of the Dukes of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua,</hi> yet carry the ſame name, and arms, and are own'd by the Dukes of <hi>Mantua</hi> as kinſmen in all their Letters, which they ſend. It is true that this kindred gives them no manner of pretence to the hereditary Succeſſion of the Duchy of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and <hi>Marquiſate</hi> of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferat:</hi> for the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> who by the Emperours conſent, at firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged them of kin to him, only upon this condition, That they ſhould be excluded from all pretences of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to that State.</p>
            <p>The Duke then was of opinion that he might ſend the Earl into <hi>Poland,</hi> not
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:154259:46"/>ſo much to make a viſit to that <hi>Marquiſeſas</hi> to be inform'd of the imployments, eſtate, and riches, and the intereſt they had in that Court; and to make his deſign hit the better, by the Earls making a longer ſtay in that journey than he expected, he order'd him to go not in the quality of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Embaſſadour, but as a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man traveller, who had no other end but to ſee the Countrey.</p>
            <p>This reſolution taken between the Duke and the Counteſs, the Earl was ſent for to receive his Commiſſion, and what elſe was neceſſary for that voyage, and to prepare himſelf. The Duke gave him many wicked and falſe reaſons, the intereſt he had in being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd fully of the eſtate, and ranck which thoſe Lords held in the Court of <hi>Poland,</hi> and told him that he had already writ Letters of Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Earl to them; in which, he had pretended that he was onely to paſs thorow that Kingdom; and had his Highneſs Commands to wait upon them from him, adding fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he had willingly ſent him in the quality of Embaſſadour to their
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:154259:46"/>King, who was his Highneſs's kinſman, but for his own convenience, and to ſave the great Charge which ſuch an Embaſſie would have coſt him, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for better profiting in his deſign, which carried him thither, he thought it more neceſſary for him to go as a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Gentleman, who had a Curioſity of ſeeing the world, than in any other quality, becauſe that in that Condition he could better inform himſelf of the eſtate thoſe Lords, without ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The Earl perceiv'd very eaſily the Dukes deſign, and although he hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly acknowledg'd the Favour his Highneſs did him in calling him to that employment of truſt; yet he could not refrain from excuſing himſelf by telling the Duke, that ſuch a Commiſſion was more fit to be given to a Page, than to a man of his Quality.</p>
            <p>The Duke who wanted neither wit nor cunning, would not receive his innumerable excuſes, although I know but one which the Duke replyed to, which the Duke ſaid might have ſerv'd had his deſign been ſomething more than a private exact information
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:154259:47"/>of the Condition in which his kinſmen were at the Court of <hi>Poland;</hi> upon which informations depended all his affairs with that Kingdom, which when he was ſatisfied of from his private voyage thither, he ſhould then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the publick Embaſſie to the <hi>Poliſh</hi> King, in which he made choice of him; and to that end had given him firſt this private Commiſſion, as moſt fit for his deſignes, and therefore he order'd him to go as ſoon as he could poſſibly get himſelf in readineſs for ſuch a Voyage; to which the Earl gave no further reply but that he ſhould do all in his power to be ready to ſerve his Highneſs that hour he ſhould appoint him for this journey; in which, he plainly diſcover'd he had no good will for him.</p>
            <p>In the beginning this order to go for <hi>Poland</hi> troubled him very much, and put a thouſand Fancies in his head, and repreſented many things to the trouble of his ſoul; but at laſt, after having well conſider'd it, he concluded it better for him to abſent himſelf than to ſtay and break his heart, by being an eye-witneſs of all the impudencies
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:154259:47"/>of his wife with the Duke, which were come to that paſs, that they made no ſcruple, ſcarce, before his face: but that kinſman of his, which I ſpoke of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, who was aged, and an experienc'd man in all the intrigues of Court, and therefore had ſo diſſwaded the Earl from this Marriage, he having ſmelt the Dukes intention, and heard the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that the Earl was to be ſent into <hi>Poland;</hi> as he was Elder than the Earl, ſo he ſpoke with more aſſurance, and without flattery told him, I ſee very well that horns will be very cheap. To which the Earl replyed, Cuckold for Cuckold, it is better to have horns made behind the back then before the Face.</p>
            <p>The Earl had fifteen days given him to prepare for his Voyage, during which he took care of all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for ſuch a journey; he took leave of all his Friends, but in a manner told them that he gave them the laſt adieu: his brothers in law counſelled him to ſerve his Highneſs with much zeal and affection; but he felt very well where his ſhoe wrung him, and thought with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelf that all their Counſels had
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:154259:48"/>no other end but, The diſhonour of his wife their own Siſter. In the mean time, he could ſo well act his part, and diſſembled ſo well, that no body ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd that he went to <hi>Poland</hi> againſt his will, he appear'd ſo gay and pleaſant; none would have believ'd, but that he made this Voyage with all the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the world. The Counteſs appear'd very indifferent to all this, and ſeem'd to be neither well nor ill pleaſed at it, knowing well that all ſhe could have ſaid would have been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſted, and therefore ſhe ſpoke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to her Husband but equivocally upon that ſubject, being certain that he was not ignorant that in all things ſhe had no intentions but thoſe of pleaſing the Duke; ſhe was more than convinc'd that her Husband be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd not one word ſhe ſaid to him, although ſhe had forc'd herſelf to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear very much afflicted at his depart; and to expreſs her joy the durſt not, believing with reaſon that exceſs of Folly would have given too publick a ſcandal to the World; however ſhe aſſur'd him, that the Duke intended to raiſe him to the higheſt Dignities the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:154259:48"/>State and Court were capable of, and that the Service which his Highneſs now deſir'd from him was, To open a way to greater Honours, to which he had deſign'd him.</p>
            <p>The Earl then parted from <hi>Caſal</hi> in the Moneth of <hi>April,</hi> accompanied by his wifes elder brother as far as <hi>Mantua,</hi> where after he had receiv'd his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs orders he paſſed the Mountains, and went on his journey.</p>
            <p>The ſame day the Duke diſpatcht a Meſſenger to the Counteſs with this note,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Heart and my All!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Earl is gon this Morning for <hi>Poland,</hi> where he will do nothing, and I intend to go from hence within two dayes, to a place where I hope to do ſomething. I ſhall reſt contented when no body works in thy Garden, which is onely worthy the labour of Princes; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me if I ſpeak ſo freely, do thou be mine, and for me, I ſhall be always thine, in ſpight of all thoſe that would trouble either of us; expect me with the ſame
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:154259:49"/>deſire I have to ſee thee, and be mine, as I am thine,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Charles.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>It will not be unneceſſary in this place to conclude the ſtory of the Earl, becauſe we ſhall not hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward have more occaſions of men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning him; I will tell you then, that he continued in <hi>Poland</hi> two Moneths without doing any thing; having not receiv'd all the remembrances, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions neceſſary touching his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations, although the Duke had given him his word to ſend them to him, but it was but a Pretext, to gain time; becauſe the Poſts that went from <hi>Mantua</hi> to <hi>Poland,</hi> went lazily, and arrived there but as late as poſſibly they could; whil'ſt in the mean time the Earl knew but too well for what reaſon the Duke had ſent him ſo far off, and into a place where he was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to be his own Comforter for all his Misfortunes; but what afflicted him moſt was, That the Duke ſent him not ſo much as the particular Inſtructions, whereby he might acquit himſelf
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:154259:49"/>aright of his Commiſſion in the Court of <hi>Poland,</hi> and alſo ſent him no money, without which it is impoſſible for ſtrangers to do any thing, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, they compaſs any thing: and therefore at laſt, he writ to the Duke and alſo his Wife theſe Letters fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which he ſent by <hi>Paris:</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Great Prince!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Yet ſtay for thoſe Letters of diſpatch, which your Highneſs made me hope I ſhould receive in this Kingdom, and yet I have not ſeen them, although two Moneths are paſs'd ſince I arrived in this Kingdom, beſides the days were ſpent in my journey hither; I have much ſhame and confuſion at being here and having no imployment, not being able to ſerve your Highneſs like a true and faithful Vaſsal: Therefore in all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility I deſire your Highneſs to ſend me with ſpeed ſomething to do, that I may teſtifie to you, with what fidelity Perſons of my Quality uſually ſerve their Sovereign, who wiſh all proſperity
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:154259:50"/>to your Highneſs, which you deſerve, I am</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your moſt humble Vaſſal, The Earl of</hi> Rovera.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The other Letter which at the ſame time he ſent to his wife was in theſe words,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My dear Spouſe!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Am ſo angry and ſo unſatisfied in being in a ſtrange Countrey, from my own Houſe, abſent from my wife, and without money, that if I had two ſouls, I would willingly give one to the Devil. His Highneſs ſent me hither with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that the Inſtructions neceſſary for me, and the Bills of Exchange, ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly follow me; but ſeeing the contrary, I know not who to complain to, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but think that I was ſent hither on no deſign, but of being rid of me. I would
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:154259:50"/>nevertheleſs flatter my ſelf, if it were poſsible, with the belief that the length of the way might perhaps be the cauſe of the ſlowneſs of my Letters, and hinder'd them from coming ſo ſoon as I expected; but for all that I cannot but afflict my ſelf, not being ignorant that thoſe people, who make uſe of my houſe in my abſence, divert themſelves, whil'ſt in the mean time I am ſuffering in the houſes of others; it troubles me not to be here, but I am vext that I have not that which was promiſed; I pray thee ſolicite his Highneſs, and ſpeak to him by word of mouth, if he is at <hi>Caſal,</hi> or by Letter, if he be at <hi>Mantua,</hi> that I may receive ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and the Duke may be ſerved; till now I have not had opportunity of ſeeing any Lady, therefore I can ſay nothing to thee of their humours nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations at preſent. This is all I can write to thee this day, deferring the reſt to another opportunity. <hi>Adieu, I embrace thee.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But let the Earl write as many Letters as he pleas'd, he ſtaid fifteen Moneths in <hi>Poland,</hi> always waiting to receive his Orders, ſcarce once ſeeing
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:154259:51"/>in all that time the Marqueſs of <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zague,</hi> or at leaſt once ſaluting him from the Duke: he bit his fingers eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day in deſpight of his being ſo cheated, he writ and writ again, but to no purpoſe in the world, and receiv'd no anſwer to all his Epiſtles but fair words, and to no end; which the Duke caus'd his Secretary to write, which circumſtance aggravated the Earls vexation, and put him out of himſelf. In fine, ſeeing he could do nothing in that Court for the ſervice of his Highneſs, and that the Duke his Maſter had very little buſineſs to treat of in that place, he made new requeſts to him, which he often repeated, for his conſent to his return to <hi>Caſal,</hi> with proteſtations of his being more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to his Highneſs at <hi>Caſal</hi> than at <hi>Poland,</hi> where he did nothing either for the Duke or himſelf, as he thought, whil'ſt in the mean time that poor man render'd all the ſervice required from him, ſince there was nothing deſired from him but his abſence.</p>
            <p>The great Liberty with which theſe two Lovers diverted themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the abſence of the Earl, made
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:154259:51"/>them invent all the means poſſible to prolong it; and ſince he renewed his deſires and preſt ſo much his return, through wearineſs of his ſtaying idle in the Court of <hi>Poland.</hi> The Duke being reſolute for his abſence a longer time, deviſed another plot worſe than the former.</p>
            <p>He ordain'd then the Earl by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Letters, That he ſhould go to the Capitol City of <hi>Perſia,</hi> where he pretended he ſhould ſtay there ſome Moneths in the quality of an Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, becauſe the intereſt of his State required ſome Correſpondence with that King, and to engage the Earl to this, he promiſed him mountains and wonders, aſſuring him that if his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes ſucceeded by his Negotiation, he ſhould want no Honours and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compences, there being none after that ſuch ſervice which he might not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to for himſelf or his heirs.</p>
            <p>The Duke ſent him there Orders, with a Letter of Exhortation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded alſo his Secretary, and his wives brothers to write to him. They obeyed the Duke, and ſent to this poor baniſh'd man Letters full of Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:154259:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>to animate him to the Dukes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, with all the affection imaginable, and fail'd not to aggravate to the Earl the honours which they preſumed would accrew to him by this voyage.</p>
            <p>When the Earl receiv'd this Order, one would have thought the Devil had taken him by the Coller; he eat his fingers with rage, and who ever had ſeen him would have thought he would alſo have devour'd his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he begun to beat his <hi>valet de Chamber,</hi> to diſcharge ſome of his Choller upon him, and that which was moſt vexatious in this buſineſs, he was the more inflam'd by the believing his reſentments ſo juſt and his extream paſſion lawful, he ſaw plainly that the Dukes onely end was to make him die of want in that long and painful voyage, that afterwards he might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy his wife with greater Liberty; he could not imagine any way what af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs the Dukes of <hi>Mantua</hi> could have with the Kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> ſo that preſs'd with grief he took a reſolution of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his footman into <hi>Italy</hi> with the ſame Letters which he had received from the Duke, reſerving to himſelf
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:154259:52"/>onely the Bills of Exchange, without giving himſelf the trouble to write to the Duke ſo much as one word of excuſe, nevertheleſs he gave this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of his two Letters of tranſport, one for his Wife, the other for his Brother in Law; The firſt was this,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Wicked Wife, the diſhonour of my Houſe, and the ruine of my Perſon,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Refrained hitherto thoſe lawful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches I could have made to thy diſſolute life, for fear of publiſhing thoſe crimes, which at leaſt ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd; but ſince thy impudencies go ſo far, as to deſtroy, I do not ſay, the quiet of my mind, (for it never teſted any ſince my cruel deſtiny joyn'd me to thee,) but that of my ſoul, which thou perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt even unto the fartheſt places of the world. I think my ſelf oblig'd now to let thee know, that I was never blind as thou believedſt me, but if I pretended to be ſo, 'twas an effect of my Prudence; I complain not of the Duke who perſecutes
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:154259:53"/>me for thy ſake; I complain of thy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty to thy Husband. Why didſt thou marry, wicked woman as thou art, if thy intentions were to be always diſhoneſt? Thou deceivedſt thy ſelf if thou did'ſt believe that at the beginnings of our Marriage I did not perceive thy abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable amour; I knew, I ſaw with great regret, although I counterfeited igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and pretended neither to ſee, nor hear, nor underſtand. It might have ſufficed thee to have diſhonour'd me at <hi>Caſal,</hi> without being ſo cruel as to drive me out of <hi>Italy.</hi> Doſt thou think I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that all theſe pretended honours are conferr'd upon me for any other end, but in conſideration of thy impudent diſhoneſt life, to mock and abuſe my ſimplicity? I underſtand it well enough, and would to God I did not at all. I forſake the name and quality of Husband, being forc'd to abandon my wife. I ſhould be the baſeſt of men to go about to ſerve a Prince, who flatters me with imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary honours, whilſt in effect he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honours me: Yes, I hope to find a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier Fortune in <hi>Barbary</hi> than in my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Countrey; and I believe that the Inhabitants of that Countrey will not
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:154259:53"/>have ſo much cruelty for me, as my Wife and my own Prince have ſhewed me in <hi>Italy;</hi> Yes, yes, I renounce thee for my wife, ſince thou wilt be a whore, and I am reſolv'd to fly thy preſence eternally, that the world may not believe I conſent to thy diſorders. I confeſs I need not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of thee, becauſe it is my ſelf I ought to blame for all my misfortunes, having been ſufficiently warned by my friends and kindred of all that I have ſuffer'd by thee, and the diſhonour thou wouldſt bring me. But in fine, ſince my deſtiny has ſent this for my ruine, I run very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly to it; and do not thou think to eſcape puniſhment, which will come upon thee one day, when thou dream'ſt not of it, and although the chaſtiſements of Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers is, like thine, deferr'd, yet it is ſure to tome; go, God will revenge me, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thee.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>He finiſh'd his Letter to the Counteſs in theſe words without Subſcription, and ſent it with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to his Brother-in-law writ in theſe terms,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:154259:54"/>
                  <p>THere is nothing I ſhould leſs have credited, than that Brothers born of an illuſtrious Bloud would have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as Raſcals in the proſtitution of their own Siſter; There is no body either in <hi>Mantua</hi> or <hi>Caſal,</hi> that is ignorant of this; It is now become the Fame of your Family, and the onely thing by which it is taken notice of; but I am very much diſpleaſed to have my reputation ingaged in it; For as for yours I deride it, ſince you have been ſo baſe to offer up to the Duke what no longer belong'd to you. That opinion of yours, That Princes can make no Cuckolds, reſembles that Gold which covers Pills, to cheat ſick people. I have alwayes lookt upon it as ſuch, and I have indur'd as much as I can; but this minute that I have not gold enough left me to cover ſuch great Pills as are preſcrib'd to me, I have no more Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and muſt complain, ſince the Duke is pleaſed I ſhall this day begin to run over the World, like a poor Pilgrim and miſerable baniſh'd man: to the end that he may enjoy your Siſter in quiet. I reſign my wife willingly to his Highneſs, and the ſhame to you; till now you have acted the part of Raſcals, and ſerv'd the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:154259:54"/>deſires of my wife: Now take to your ſelves the employment of ſerving your Siſter. This is all ſhall be ſaid to you from him that gives you abſolutely his ſhare in the ſhame, that you may poſſeſs it all; he flyes from the company of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted adulterous woman, and from the Pimps her Brothers; underſtand me as well as I underſtand both of you.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe were the laſt Letters which the Earl writ to <hi>Caſal,</hi> with which the Duke lookt upon himſelf ſo ſenſibly offended, having got them both into his hands, that he ſwore in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes preſence to be revenged: Many were of opinion that he was quickly after that ſatisfied in his vengeance he intended on the Earl, becauſe that minute he made his Oath, he diſpatch'd many Letters, giving order to follow him, and to learn what was become of him, of whom ſince that time there was no news heard, which was the cauſe ſo many believ'd he was kill'd by the Dukes <hi>Orders,</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this laſt common opinion, becauſe that Prince had not ſo black a ſoul; and I rather think he was ſatisfied
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:154259:55"/>enough with ordering him to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd only by ſending him far enough off his State; ſome were of opinion that he went into <hi>Swede,</hi> and under a diſguize chang'd his Religion and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a <hi>Lutheran;</hi> and ſome believe he lives at this day in ſome little place he purchas'd with thoſe thouſand Piſtols which the Duke ſent him by Bills of Exchange for his Voyage into <hi>Perſia:</hi> Others pretend he has been ſeen in <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall</hi> not five years ſince, which is not certified credibly. But whatever is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of him, there has not any thing been heard of him ſince that time, and at <hi>Caſal</hi> there is nothing ſpoken of him good or bad, and therefore we will talk no more of him, but here conclude the life of that unfortunate Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</p>
            <p>Let us now return to that poor Princeſs, almoſt forſaken by her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, in all things but outward ſhew; who ſeeing her ſelf thus treated by the Duke her Husband, for the love of an infamous woman, and one ſo much below her in Birth, that there is no other compariſon between them to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:154259:55"/>be made but what is given between that of a Prince and a ſlave; ſo that it was very difficult for her to hinder her ſelf from loudly complaining of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, and the more by ſeeing every day her husbands affection grow colder for her, and increaſe to that wicked woman, who alone poſſeſs'd his heart. This afflicted Ducheſs was deſperate at all the abominable tricks which from day to day were plaid the Earl beyond the Seas, onely to leave his wife at more Liberty with the Duke; and her affliction was very much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed when ſhe was inform'd of his deſpair, which had cauſed him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce abſolutely the ſerving that Court any more, and never to return to <hi>Caſal,</hi> nor yet into any part of <hi>Italy;</hi> and ſince ſhe heard by the whiſpering murmurs of the Courtiers, that the Duke angry at this procedure of the Earl had reſolv'd to purſue him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge where-ever he went; in pity to this poor Lord, ſhe went to ask his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of the Duke, and to that effect ſhe ſet before his eyes the example of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> driven from his Kingdom, not ſo much by the perſecution of <hi>Abſalom</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:154259:56"/>his ſon, as the decree of Heaven, to puniſh him for Adultery, which he had committed with <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and that horrid execrable and barbarous mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Uriah</hi> her husband, adding, That that Prophet had not ſo violently per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted <hi>Uriah,</hi> as his Highneſs had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued the Earl; nor had liv'd ſo long a time in Adultery with <hi>Bathſheba</hi> as he had liv'd with the Counteſs. The Duke, angry at theſe ſolicitations, roſe up from the bed where he was ſitting, whil'ſt the Ducheſs was talking to him, and walking to the Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door, gave her no other anſwer than this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam, that which men believ'd in the Old Teſtament to be a ſin, all Princes account this day a gallantry:</hi> and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, he went away.</p>
            <p>The Ducheſs ſeeing all her words unprofitable, and work'd nothing upon the heart of the Duke, which was har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der than any rock, to all Counſels that were given him to take him off his ſcandalous living; ſhe reſolv'd at laſt to try another way, and employ greater
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:154259:56"/>ſtrengths than her own, though ſhe went far to fetch them. She knew ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well the veneration of the Duke for the Senate of <hi>Venice,</hi> and ſhe had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten heard him profeſs his conſiderable Obligations to that illuſtrious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, with which he held great Correſpondence for the intereſt and conſideration of his own State. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe took the occaſion of petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Senate in private to interpoſe their authority, to deliver her from her troubles, and to take the Duke from his ſcandalous way of life with the Counteſs.</p>
            <p>That Senate, who does nothing without great Caution and Prudence, did not think this a neceſſary buſineſs for the whole body of the Counſel to take notice of, therefore they order'd <hi>Monſieur Juſtiniani</hi> to undertake it as a particular man, and to uſe all poſſible diligence in the affair: That Lord did not fail to receive that Commiſſion with much reſpect and ſubmiſſion, but he was not without fear that he ſhould be able to effect nothing to the ſatisfaction of the Senate, nor of the Archducheſs; he nevertheleſs omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:154259:57"/>no opportunity of ſurprizing the Duke, to talk to him about it, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found an hour fit for his purpoſe, he begun to talk of this Commiſſion with an admirable Eloquence back'd with Reaſons ſo ſolid as never yet was ſeen come from the tongue of that Excellent Oratour; but all his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and ſtrong Reaſons were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable; all the Diſcourſes of this Illuſtrious Lord producing no effect, and made no impreſſion in the heart of the Duke, who anſwer'd reſolutely to that Oracle of the Senate, that there was but one remedy to cure ſo great a ſickneſs, and that was, To ſend for an Executioner from <hi>Venice,</hi> to cut his heart out of his breaſt, becauſe as long as it ſtaid there, it muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity be the Counteſſes, and without depriving him of his heart, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to take from him the love he bore to the Counteſs. After that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <hi>Juſtiniani</hi> found it to no purpoſe to preſs him further, and to undertake any more againſt ſo great a wilfulneſs, as he diſcover'd in the Duke.</p>
            <p>That Prince then ſhutting his eyes to all kind of Conſiderations, lived
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:154259:57"/>with the Counteſs like a Husband with his Wife, he carried her along with him when he went a Hunting, and alſo to the Palace royal of <hi>Mantua,</hi> where his wife the Archducheſs alſo lay, he eat with the Counteſs, ſlept with her, and careſſed her in the preſence of all his Courtiers, almoſt before the face of that poor Princeſs his wife, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe ſaw not what they ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily did, did not fail to hear of it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſtory of what paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe two Lovers brought to her every day, all the Embaſſadours, the Gentlemen, Noblemen, as alſo all the Ladies of <hi>Mantua,</hi> admired the great Goodneſs of this Princeſs, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with ſo much Patience ſo great an injury, or to ſay better, ſuch an afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of heart; for to ſay the truth, that diſhoneſt love of the Dukes brought more glory to the Ducheſs than any diſgrace, becauſe ſhe in that Patience expreſſed ſo great a vertue, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing jealouſie, and mocking at all thoſe carnal pleaſures of Matrimony, and letting the world ſee that all her trouble and mortification proceeded onely from no other cauſe than the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:154259:58"/>ſin her Husband committed, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are not to call that Patience of hers a corporeal injury, but an affliction of Spirit.</p>
            <p>There wanted no Ladies nor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men about the Court, who counſell'd the Ducheſs from time to time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge her ſelf of that Proſtitute, by one of thoſe Draughts ſo common in <hi>Italy,</hi> as the onely remedy to put an end not onely to her own affliction, but alſo the Duke her husbands adultery, and to take away the diſhonour of the Counteſſes Family, beſides the depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Court of its great trouble.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt there were two perſons of very large Conſciences, as one may ſay, wide as a Friars ſleeve, offered themſelves voluntarily to do this deed, the one was a Tailor, who proffered to end the Counteſſes life with the Shot of a Harquebuz, which he would in private Shoot at her, and no body ſhould know of it, and that he would take great care in chuſing his time, asking for recompence of that action but two hundred Piſtols, to keep him in any place he ſhould be forc'd to fly to, it not being poſſible after doing
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:154259:58"/>that to think of returning back to his own houſe; or if they thought that ſumme too much for him, he askt no more than a good Recommendation to the Archduke, to be favourably treated with him.</p>
            <p>The other perſon that offered to diſpatch the Counteſs was a Lady and her kinſwoman, honourable by reaſon of her age, who believing her ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in the diſ-reputation the Counteſs had brought upon her Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and touched with ſhame and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion for the Archducheſs, offered her ſelf alſo to poiſon this adulterous Counteſs, ſo privately that none ſhould ever know it.</p>
            <p>But that poor Princeſs who lookt upon all thoſe Miſeries, as being by the permiſſion of Heaven, and receiving them as coming from the hands of God, did not onely blame thoſe bloudy reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and tragical deſignes of thoſe murtherers, but ſhe alſo forbid them for ever the preſenting themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her with thoſe Propoſitions, and it is ſaid that one day, as ſhe was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing with her Confeſſour (in the preſence of the Governeſs of her
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:154259:59"/>houſe) of the ſcandalous life the Duke liv'd with that Counteſs, and the Propoſals had been offered her of revenging that adultery. That Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour told her, <hi>That great perſons might commit a ſmall evil, to deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from a greater.</hi> Which the Ducheſs ſcarce heard him ſay, but gueſſing well his deſign, which was onely to carry her to revenge, ſhe quickly replyed, <hi>We had rather ſuffer the Counteſs to live with her ſin, than to let her die with ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words ſufficiently teſtified the great goodneſs and admirable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that excellent Princeſs, with which ſhe indured all her diſgrace ſo well, that ſhe took more delight in ſuffering, whil'ſt others were pleas'd, than ſhe could have taken ſatisfaction amongſt all kind of proſperities, whil'ſt other people had been unhappy; alſo ſhe never went about to buy her own repoſe by a Crime, and ſatisfie the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of her body by an offence ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall to her ſoul, which makes me believe that God will take her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his particular care during her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency, and ſo much the more, becauſe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:154259:59"/>ſhe prefers the intereſt of her Maker before all thoſe of the world.</p>
            <p>The Emperour and the Archduke ſent by their Ambaſſadours a deſire to the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> that he would a little open his eyes, an conſider the great ſcandal he liv'd in, even in the fight of all the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting that they propounded this to him not out of reſentment, but were preſs'd to it out of the tender affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they bore to his perſon. They alſo aſſur'd him that they had not been ſolicited to this motion by the Princeſs their kinſwoman, who complain'd not in the leaſt to them of ill treatment, but on the contrary, proteſted to them that the Duke her Husband honour'd her very much, and except in the bed neer him, to which the Counteſs alone was priviledged, the Duke us'd her with all the civility imaginable, as well in private as publick. Therefore the Emperourr and the Archduke had no cauſe to complain of any thing, and leſs yet, in that it happen'd contrary in this ſcandalous life of the Dukes, to that which ordinarily paſſes in ſuch a caſe by many that uſe their wives ill,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:154259:60"/>for the ſake of their Miſtreſſes. For the Duke contrary to other men, was grown ſo crafty, that he knew how to act cunningly by apparently ſatisfying his wife before the world, and taking his private pleaſures with the Counteſs; ſo that it was not eaſie for any to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any change in the looks of that chaſte Princeſs, but rather much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and pleaſure. It is true, that outſide Friendſhip in appearance ought not to be imputed to the care and prudence of the Duke ſo much as to the goodneſs of his wife; who being endowed with a ſingular vertue, and an extraordinary prudence, could hide her grief, and expreſs no ſignes of trouble in her Face, although her heart was preſs'd down with affliction.</p>
            <p>The Court of <hi>Rome</hi> received with much diſpleaſure the news of this ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous adultery, and the trouble it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived was aggravated by the quality of that great Perſon, who was guilty of that publick diſorder; and therefore it gave Orders to the Superiours of the Convents at <hi>Caſal</hi> and <hi>Mantua</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn the Preachers to exaggerate the nature of this Crime in their Pulpits,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:154259:60"/>whil'ſt in the mean time the Duke ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd the World to Talk, and the Monks to Croſs themſelves, and went to Sermons when the Fancy took him, and hearkned to what he liked; upon which, it hapned, that a Father of the Order of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> by in indiſcrete Zeale, having too much reflected upon the Perſon of the Duke, and too open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoke of the Counteſs, found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo intangled, he was conſtrain'd to quit <hi>Mantua,</hi> till he was forc'd to Swear, That for time to come he would change his Note, and in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting the Vices of Princes, he would henceforward uſe more diſcretion.</p>
            <p>The Dukes Confeſſor was alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to remember his Highneſs ſometimes of the Obligation he had to leave off his ſcandalous life; (as if the greateſt evil of that Crime lay in the Scandal of it:) but that good Father lov'd better to be in the good graces of a Prince, Adulterous and Criminal, then Enemy of a Juſt and Innocent one: And furthermore, he was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent, that when he Confeſt him, he eaſily gave him Abſolution; Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the fault upon the weakneſs of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:154259:61"/>our Nature: In truth, there are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors in theſe dayes, that are cauſe of the loſs of many Princes; For, they being Ambitious to Domineer over the other Brothers of the Convent by their Princes Favour; they would be content (rather then loſe that Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) not onely to ſend their Princes to Hell, but alſo go themſelves to the Devil; neglecting the Duties of their Place, and their Paſtoral Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, in excuſing the Faults which theſe Illuſtrious Sinners commit.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs alſo receiv'd from time to time her ſecret Mortifications; for the Biſhop, ſollicited perhaps from <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Arch-Dutcheſs, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to her ſometimes the condition of her life, threatning to refuſe to give her the Holy Sacrament at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> but it was but Threats, to which ſhe heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned very little, and which gave her but little trouble, becauſe ſhe was confident they would never be perform'd, for fear of diſobliging his Highneſs; and the more, becauſe the excuſed her ſelf, by laying the fault upon the Duke, ſaying to him that came to ſpeak to her from the Biſhop, That being
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:154259:61"/>born a Subject, ſhe could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Duke not to ſee her any more, becauſe he would do her that Honour.</p>
            <p>I cannot forbear in this place to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late an Accident, no leſs curious then Politick, which hapned during theſe paſſages.</p>
            <p>My Lord Biſhop of <hi>Caſſal</hi> had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken a thing believed impoſſible by all the World, which was, to find out a remedy to divert the Duke from this Love of the Counteſs; which was ſo Publick, that there could not be a greater between two perſons Marryed: but the whil'ſt he labour'd by I know not what Political and Paſtoral Zeal, he found the end of his dayes in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of a Scandal; this Death of his regreted by all: he having been a Prelate of an exemplar life, and held worthy of ſo eminent a charge in the Church, in which he had alwayes ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf with great Zeale.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs was not very ſorry, ſeeing her ſelf by that delivered from the apprehenſion, of loſing the Dukes good Graces, of which ſhe was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, by the ſtrong exhortations of that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:154259:62"/>Biſhop. On the contrary, ſhe had no ſooner heard the news of the Death of the Biſhop, but ſpeaking to her Siſter the Counteſs <hi>Louize,</hi> ſhe ſaid to her, the poor Biſhop is dead, for ayming too much at Fifty-Cuffs againſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; ſhe meant by that, to ſhew it was all one, to Fight againſt Heaven, and to endeavour to ruine her Favour with the Duke.</p>
            <p>The Earl her Brother going alſo to talke to her upon the Subject of the Biſhops Death, ſaid to her, Siſter, you have loſt a great Enemy at leaſt, if he that is his Succeſſor prove not of his humour: To which ſhe anſwer'd; He ſhall be my Friend, or nothing.</p>
            <p>The Biſhops Funerals were ſcarce ended, but, as well from the State of <hi>Mantua,</hi> as <hi>Rome,</hi> there ſtarted up ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretenders to his place; The Pope pretended a right in the chuſing of a Biſhop for <hi>Caſal,</hi> in the State of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua,</hi> becauſe all knew very well, that although the right of making a Biſhop of <hi>Caſal</hi> belonged to his Holyneſs, yet there was no great ſatisfaction to be found, for any that ſhould be made without the Dukes conſent: It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:154259:62"/>certain, that to be a Biſhop of any Town, againſt the Good-will of their Sovereign, it is no other, then to ruine any Mans Fortune, and keep him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in trouble: There is no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that will accept it without having at the leaſt the nomination of the Prince, or elſe a recommendation from him; And for this reaſon, there were as well at <hi>Mantua</hi> as at <hi>Caſal,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to that Biſhoprick, ſeeking to the Duke for a Nomination, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation from his Highneſs.</p>
            <p>Amongſt many others, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voſt of <hi>Miroglio</hi> had a mind to this Biſhoprick, and it was very eaſie for him to attain it, becauſe no body dream't of him, for the way he took was better, and very different from thoſe that the reſt of the Pretenders had taken; he addreſſes himſelf to the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> with whom he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes held a very good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and now ſought her Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation by ſubmiſſions and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, with extraordinary Proffers; he promis'd her a Purſe with a thouſand Crowns in it to buy her a Diamond; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting to her, that he would willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:154259:63"/>teſign the Croſs into her hands; ſhewing her by that, that he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner do any thing which ſhould not be as ſhe would have it, and to her ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: he forgot not to intreate her, that for all theſe conſiderations ſhe would imploy all her intereſt with his Highneſs, to obtain his Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to his Holyneſs.</p>
            <p>This occaſion lookt ſo faire, that the Counteſs would not neglect it: Therefore ſhe promis'd him to imploy all her credit to bring his deſign about, ſo well, that he ſhould be ſatisfyed with her endeavours; ſhe went then to her Well-Beloved, and repreſented to him, how neceſſary it was to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to have a Prelate at <hi>Caſal,</hi> of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Humour then the former; who, under a colour of Zeal, ſhould not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>upt the repoſe which their Loves injoy'd, ſince the death of the laſt Biſhop; telling him further, that <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglio</hi> was a Man of a perfect prudence, and worthy of that Biſhoprick; ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe words often in the Dukes eares, My Heart, I deſire thee to act ſo, that this affair ſucceed in behalf of this Gallant Man; and certainly,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:154259:63"/>he was alwayes lookt upon as ſuch; for, being a Prelate, he acquitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his charge very well, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues ſtill to do ſo; and although he ſalutes every Body with a Smiling Countenance, and all kind of affabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; and that in his ordinary Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he ſtill mingles ſome jeaſting word or other: he nevertheleſs with all that forgets not to Govern the Church and his Dioceſs extreamly well.</p>
            <p>The Duke, who of himſelf was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to favour that Lord, not onely conſented to the requeſt of his Well-beloved in his behalfe, but engag'd himſelf further to act with all his power.</p>
            <p>After this teſtimony of the Dukes good will, the Counteſs willing to try the conſtancy of this Lord <hi>Miraglio,</hi> and to diſcover what his Thoughts would be (if he arriv'd to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick) of her Amour with the Duke, ſent for him, and after having aſſur'd him of the Dukes Favour and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the end he deſir'd it, ſhe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him the great imprudence of the deceaſed Prelate, who, not content to injoy his Biſhoprick in peace, which
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:154259:64"/>he held by the Dukes Favour, would trouble the repoſe of His Highneſs, in ſeeking to make him paſs for an Adulterer.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Miroglio,</hi> who, penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the quick into the Soul of this Crafty woman, anſwer'd her like a Gallant Man; for, after he had very much condemn'd the procedure of the dead Prelate, he Swore to her, that if ever he receiv'd the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, he would never do any thing, but what ſhould pleaſe the Duke and her ſelf; furthermore, he added, That the Sins of Princes were but ſmall in the eyes of God; and in fine, he brought many other ſuch kind of reaſons, and perhaps better to reach his end, and compaſs his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, onely to appear blind to the Dukes Scandalous Life, and Publick Adultery.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs was not unſatisfied with this Diſcourſe, and tolerating that Lord, ſhe made him ſo many advantagious Promiſes, that he part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from her very well contented, and pleaſed the more with the laſt words of the Counteſs, which were, That he
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:154259:64"/>was as ſure of being Biſhop, as he was certain that the Duke was Lord of <hi>Caſal,</hi> and Soveraign of his State.</p>
            <p>The time of parting for <hi>Rome</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come, my Lord <hi>Miroglio</hi> was at the Palace, to obtain the Letters of Recommendation from His Highneſs, and receive the neceſſary Orders; but the Duke, to let him ſee that he conſider'd in that Choice, more the Intereſt of his Beloved, ſent for him, and told him, My Lord, you ſhall receive from the Counteſs all you wiſh: To whom he anſwer'd, with a low Congee, The Hands of ſuch a Lady could bring him nothing but good Fortune.</p>
            <p>The Duke Writ divers Letters to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> to recommend the Intereſt of this Pretender to the Biſhoprick; but, amongſt the reſt, that which he writ to his Holyneſs, was ſo much to his advantage, he could not reaſonably deſire one great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and becauſe the Counteſs gave him this Letter open, I will here give you the Contents to ſatisfie the Curioſity of the Reader.</p>
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:154259:65"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt Holy <hi>FATHER.</hi>
                     </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>AFter having moſt Humbly Kiſſed your Feet, with all the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my Heart; I Salute your <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> with all the Humility of my Soul; recommending in he mean time to the Politick and Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiatick Zeal of Your <hi>Holineſs,</hi> the Intereſts of my Lord <hi>Miroglio,</hi> Provoſt of this Town, and a Man very much beloved in my houſe; be aſpires to this Vacant Biſhoprick, and if I am not deceiv'd, I believe his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit renders him worthy enough of it; the time of the Warr, which makes this Town liable to great ſuffering, both within and without, obliges me to be more earneſt with Your <hi>Holineſs,</hi> to conſider the Perſon I recommend to you, and Create Biſhop of <hi>Caſal</hi> this Subject, whom I look upon as my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Friend, and a Man qualified to remove all Cauſes of Jealouſie, which uſually grow from the Introduction of Prelates who are ſtrangers, into ſuch
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:154259:65"/>eminent Places; and therefore I deſire Your <hi>Holineſs,</hi> with the Humility of a Son, to Grant me with this Grace Your Fatherly Benediction.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Counteſs had no ſooner given this Letter to Monſieur <hi>Miroglio,</hi> and the others addreſſed to ſome of the Cardinals, then he went for <hi>Rome;</hi> where, being arriv'd, he deliver'd the Letters, and Sollicited his Affaires and Intereſts with a care ſuitable to his Pretenſions; and ſuch as you may gueſs by the uſual diligence of thoſe who aſpire to the like Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>The other Pretenders, who were very numerous, ſeeing how conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his Recommendations were, and that his Party was the ſtrongeſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun <hi>A la mode</hi> of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> to Croſs him, and with all their power endeavoured to exclude him, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proofes of his inſufficiency, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring againſt his Perſon; and which was worſe, publiſhing many things againſt his Reputation.</p>
            <p>There were two chiefe Reaſons which they ſet up, to diſcountenance
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:154259:66"/>his Pretenſions; the Firſt was, That there was no regard to be taken to thoſe Letters of Recommendation procured by an Adulterous Woman, and bought of her with a great Sum of ready Mony: And the Second was, That it would be Scandalous to make Coſin of a Heretick a Biſhop, who alſo carry'd the ſame name of her Family: But not to leave the Reader in doubt upon this Particular; I will explain it all in two word.</p>
            <p>Twelve yeares before this, <hi>Don Mario Miroglio,</hi> Canon of the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Church of <hi>Caſal,</hi> neer Kinſman to Lord Provoſt <hi>Miroglio,</hi> was retir'd from that Town to <hi>Geneva,</hi> to the great diſpleaſure of the Chapter, and the Houſe of <hi>Miroglio,</hi> who ſpar'd for nothing to bring him back from whence he was fled but he, deriding all their Remonſtrances, chang'd his Religion, to embrace that which is Profeſſed at <hi>Geneva;</hi> and was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Marryed; he dyed ſome time after, leaving two Male Children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, to Eternize his Name in that Church ſo contrary to the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:154259:66"/>
            <p>The whole ſacred Colledge was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of that by his enemies, who had the ſame pretenſion with him, and above all they chiefly inform'd the Cardinal <hi>Sforza,</hi> as he that ſpoke the freelieſt, and ſpared not the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when he was to give his advice, and they were not deceiv'd, for the Cardinal <hi>Sforza,</hi> going to the Pope, ſought at firſt to snake a way into his thoughts, to alter his reſolution of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Miroglio</hi> Biſhop, and ſeeing for all his endeavours, that all things went on that Lords ſide, he was reſolute, and could not forbear, ſaying one day to the Pope in a full Conſiſtory,</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Moſt holy Father!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF your Holineſs reſolves to make the brother of it heretick a Biſhop at leaſt, let it not be the pimp of an adulterous woman.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Pope notwithſtanding knowing that Cardinals humour, ſaid onely to him, that he was very well acquainted with the merits of the Lord <hi>Miroglio.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:154259:67"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Miroglio</hi> then made Biſhop, contrary to the expectation of all the world, and to the great diſcontent of his enemies, he gave many thanks to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, beſides giving her the thouſand Crowns, which he had promis'd her before, and I will not ſpeak of the many Preſents he made to divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the Dukes Court.</p>
            <p>This Prelate wanted for no civility nor reſpect for the Counteſs, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd her very often with his viſites, ſtaying many afternoons with her, whil'ſt the Prince was at <hi>Mantua;</hi> for when the Duke was at <hi>Caſal,</hi> her houſe was forbid to all the world, except the Duke, to whom it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong'd to Court that Fair one; one day however, as the Biſhop was going out of the Counteſſes houſe, to whom he had been making a viſit, he met the Duke, who ſaid to him, My Lord Biſhop, it were better that your Greatneſs ſhould enter, and I ſhould go out from this houſe, then for me to go in, and you to go out. He ſaid this onely to give the Biſhop to underſtand, that he who was a Prelate ought to give the Counteſs the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:154259:67"/>of her ſins, which he was going to commit with her.</p>
            <p>But to return to the Ducheſs, who was, as one may ſay, forſaken; you muſt know that ſeeing all things de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate as to the converſation of the Prince her Husband, ſhe reſolv'd to give her foul ſome reſt, to let him do whatſoever pleas'd him, without ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take any notice, and to give theſe Lovers leave to take all their ſwing, with a full reſolve to mind no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for the future, and to take no further care, importuning them no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, all ſhe had done having been to little purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The greateſt favour ſhe had deſir'd from her Husband had been, That he would content himſelf with the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal he gave to his own State, without doing ſuch groſs things, to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the diſcourſe of other Nations, and the ſcorn' of the Courts of other Princes; and indeed the Duke and the Counteſs liv'd in ſuch liberty, that it was verily believ'd that there was a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate divorce between the Duke and his Ducheſs, ſo that by the conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them both, their marriage was
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:154259:68"/>broke; and that he had after that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately married the Counteſs, which nevertheleſs was very far from truth; but it was impoſſible to ſhut the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon peoples mouths, as long as this ſcandal was ſo publike. The Duke cared not to go one ſtep without the Counteſs, they eat and drunk together, and they never went to take the Air without one another; if the Duke went from <hi>Mantua</hi> to <hi>Caſal,</hi> or to <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua</hi> from <hi>Caſal,</hi> he always carried the Counteſs with him in the Coach, Alone; and for her part, ſhe could not in the journey ſuffer her ſelf one minute to forſake him who was more to her than ſhe was to her ſelf. I leave theſe conſiderations to the Impartial Reader, and not to the Lover, or whoſoever he is that reads this Book, and is troubled with amorous fancies; what followed theſe privacies.</p>
            <p>The impudence of this bold woman grew to that exceſs, that not content to have ſpoild the good Judgment, Nature, and the Prudence of the Duke, in ſeeking to govern him her own way, and injoy him according to the motions of her brutiſh appetites,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:154259:68"/>and believing her ſelf not bolig'd to keep any meaſures, triumphing inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently over her ſhame, it ſeem'd very little to her to be talk'd on onely in her own Countrey, although ſhe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried much in that; but ſhe chiefly aſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at the publiſhing her favour with the Duke in other Nations, deſiring they ſhould know how much ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed with him above all that the greateſt Favorites could ever pretend to from any Prince; though ſhe a little fear'd that the ſtories of her ſin and adultery might come to their ears; She was ambitious that fame ſhould publiſh her in all places, and that not onely the people of <hi>Montferrat,</hi> and the <hi>Mantuans,</hi> but all <hi>Italy</hi> (not to ſpeak of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Europe</hi>) ſhould know that ſhe accompanied the Duke every where, that they ſhould ſee her play, and walk with him, and be eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes, that ſhe ſlept with this Prince when ſhe pleas'd.</p>
            <p>To ſatisfie this ambition ſhe deſir'd his Highneſs, that he would carry her to <hi>Venice,</hi> to ſee the Solemnity which is there upon <hi>Aſcenſion</hi>-day, but the Duke, who weighed all things with
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:154259:69"/>more prudence, promis'd he would ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie her, in ſending with her what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſoever ſhe pleas'd to have in her company, except himſelf; not thinking it fit for him to appear with her before the Senate, ſince upon her account he had receiv'd a private rebuke from them, as I told you before, but ſhe who onely ſought to appear there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the ſtrangers that were at that time at <hi>Venice,</hi> and to pleaſe her ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more than her curioſity, could not receive his offer; and told him plainly that ſhe would go with no other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany than his Highneſs. In fine ſhe knew ſo well how to charm him with her careſſes; and gave him ſo many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that ſhe made him reſolve to go himſelf, and carry her with him, as ſhe deſired.</p>
            <p>The Duke would make this Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age <hi>incognito,</hi> but his Miſtreſs would carry her Siſter the Counteſs <hi>Lovize,</hi> and three other Ladies with her, all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well dreſt, and with them ſome Maids of Honour and waiting Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, which was the reaſon that thoſe who were not acquainted with the Amours of theſe two paſſionate
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:154259:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lovers took this fair Pilgrim for the Archducheſs, who went <hi>incognito,</hi> and to ſay the truth, this Voyage could not be made with more magnificence nor joy for her, ſhe might have been called a little triumphant Princeſs, who had alwayes the Prince at her ſide, who led her by the hand, as well in publike as private, and ſhe was ſo over-joyed to ſee her ſelf honour'd and ſerved by all the Courtiers, who treated her as if ſhe had been their true and lawful Soveraign Princeſs, that it is impoſſible to find words to expreſs her ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>The noiſe of their arrival in <hi>Venice</hi> was quickly ſpread through all the town, and curioſity carried immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the town in crouds to the ſtreets, to ſee theſe two Lovers who were ſo much talkt of, not onely through all <hi>Italy,</hi> but every where elſe, the ſtreets were fill'd with a number almoſt infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite of perſons of both ſexes, who crouded one another to behold with how great a grace the Duke led the Counteſs by the hand in the ſight of all the people.</p>
            <p>It is confidently, ſpoken that this
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:154259:70"/>Prince ſpent in this Voyage more than three thouſand Piſtols in many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents which he made, he gave amongſt the Ladies of his troop five hundred Crowns, and the reſt to the Counteſs, who coveted all that ſhe ſaw in every ſhop amongſt the Merchants; and when ſhe took notice of any rarity, which was commended in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſhe ſpared no careſſes nor flatteries to the Duke to perſwade him to buy that knack upon which ſhe had ſet her heart. It is certainly believ'd, that the Duke till that hour had not found any ſign of covetouſneſs in the Counteſs, and till then ſhe had never expreſs'd a deſire of any thing beſides the love of her Gallant; but the Air of <hi>Venice</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd her nature, and what ever ſhe had a mind to, the Duke never contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted her deſires, he was ſo far from denying her any thing, that one day as they paſt by a Jewellers ſhop, they ſhew'd this fair Lady a great number of precious ſtones, amongſt which there was a little Roſe of Diamonds, round beſet with little Golden Eaglets, which held out their Bills to kiſs one another, which ſeem'd almoſt the arms of the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:154259:70"/>houſe of <hi>Gonzague,</hi> the Counteſs then looking ſtedfaſtly upon that Jewel, and with great deſires, without daring to ask it, for fear of being too impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, the price being more than four thouſand Crowns, with ſome careſſes and flatteries, without once opening her mouth to beg it, ſhe oblig'd her loving captive to give it her with theſe words, <hi>I ſhall not be much troubled to part with all my money to her, to whom I have given all my heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In returning home they went to <hi>Padua,</hi> where by chance that day the Comedy of <hi>Joſeph</hi> was acted in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, which the Duke would ſee; he went thither with the Counteſs, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by all his people, and placed himſelf with the other Ladies of his company in a Box over againſt the Stage, where he always held his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs in his arms, imbracing her in the face of the whole Aſſembly, who took not their eyes of them one moment. In the mean time, when the Scene where the wife of <hi>Potiphar</hi> is repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, forcing of <hi>Joſeph</hi> to ſleep with her, and particularly at that place where that example of Chaſtity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:154259:71"/>her, and flying away leaves her his Cloak. The Counteſs turning to the Duke ſaid, <hi>I cannot praiſe this young man, for having thus left an affamiſh'd Lady;</hi> to which the Duke anſwer'd, <hi>All the world is not ſo charitable, nor ſo complaiſant, as I am for thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſcandal which all <hi>Lombardy</hi> ſuffer'd by this Voyage, diſpleaſed the Ducheſs very much, and ſhe could not refrain the expreſſing her reſentments to the Duke; but ſince her words accompanied with her ordinary Mild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs had nothing of indignation in them, they made no impreſſions upon the heart of her husband, who had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſacrific'd her to the Counteſs, with whom he liv'd in ſuch a manner that the world were almoſt perſwaded that there had paſs'd ſome Clandeſtine Marriage between them, which was the Cauſe of no ſmall diſpleaſure amongſt the people who were very much afflicted to ſee their Prince ſo effeminated,</p>
            <p>In the mean time the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> murmur'd, and bore with much impatience, not onely the life which the Duke led with the Counteſs, but
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:154259:71"/>alſo were more troubled at the Popes ſilence, who ſought not to remedy theſe ſcandals: this noiſe and theſe impatiencies increas'd by the return of Cardinal <hi>Leomelini,</hi> who came from this Legation at <hi>Bologne,</hi> who having had ſome conteſts with the Duke, ſought a revenge: and ſince we are come to ſpeak of that particular, I think it will no be from the purpoſe to touch, in paſſing by, upon it as briefly as I can poſſible.</p>
            <p>The Nobility of <hi>Bologne</hi> had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited the Duke to ſee ſome Comical repreſentations that were to be in the Town, with a magnificence and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration extraordinary; and becauſe the Duke could not longer live without his Counteſs, nor ſcarce go four ſteps without having her in his Company, he carried her again with him, as if ſhe had been his wife, to ſee thoſe ſhews aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen, that belong'd to the Legate Cardinal <hi>Leomelini,</hi> could not refrain from murmuring with ſome kind of ſcorn and mocks to the Dukes actions, who with an univerſal ſcandal carried along with him an Adultereſs,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:154259:72"/>even into the Towns of the reſort of the Eccleſiaſtical State; on the other ſide thoſe who belong'd to the Duke ſeeing themſelves oblig'd to defend the reputation of their Sovereign, after many injurious words on both ſides, came to blows, to the great diſpleaſure of the Nobility in that Town, who ſaw themſelves oblig'd in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture to take the Dukes part, againſt thoſe of the Cardinal, ſo that the Duke ſeeing himſelf affronted, ſent to complain to his Eminence, who in ſtead of ſatisfaction in puniſhing the beginners, protected his men, and threatned the Duke himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Duke went out then from <hi>Bologne,</hi> all in rage, with deſign to cauſe the Cardinal to be murder'd in his Coach, and to that end he ſent upon <hi>Good Friday</hi> twenty four men well armed, who, being enter'd the Town, diſcharg'd at the ſame time many Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols into the Legates Windows, not that they had deſigns to kill, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front him; all the inhabitants were in a maze at the boldneſs of thoſe Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, who hazarded their lives with ſo such confidence they ſaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:154259:72"/>nevertheleſs without receiving any hurt, although they were purſued by the Guards.</p>
            <p>The Gentlemen of <hi>Bologne,</hi> and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly thoſe who had invited his Highneſs to <hi>Bologne,</hi> perceiving that the Duke was very angry, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any further miſchief that might happen through this diſorder, ſent word to Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> to the end that the might hinder it, who, making uſe of his ordinary prudence by a Maxime of Policy, took that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment from the Cardinal, pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he would give him one more ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to his Eſtate, and put in his place the Cardinal <hi>Farneſe,</hi> who was of the laſt creation, and friend to the Duke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leomelini</hi> knew preſently from whence this change came, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without looſing time returned to <hi>Rome</hi> to be revenged of this injury, which, to ſpeak truth, was an affront; to arrive at this deſign, he began pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to inform all the Conclave of the Cardinals, and his Holineſs alſo, of that ſhameful life which the Duke lived with the Counteſs, and the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:154259:73"/>great ſcandal which it gave to all <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardy.</hi> That ſong which the Courtiers ſung quickly ſpread over the whole Town of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo that in the ſtreets no other thing was talked on.</p>
            <p>That Cardinal was very importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to have this Duke proceeded againſt by way of Excommunication, giving them to underſtand with his uſual authority, that if they ſuffered ſuch an adultery to be unpuniſhed, the Hereticks without doubt would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and the holy Chair would ſuffer a great blow to its reputation, and in fine would condemn the Church for tolerating and permitting adultery.</p>
            <p>But the Duke inform'd of all theſe things, cauſed it to be told the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Leomelini, That he would teach him to ſpeak, if he would not learn to hold his tongue.</hi> For all this his Eminence chang'd not his note, who being not accuſtomed to tongue injuries, repeated always the ſame ſong, and very far from hearkning to peace, or to ſeek it, the more that he ſaw himſelf threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he repeated his complaints the more to the Pope and his Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals.</p>
            <pb n="139" facs="tcp:154259:73"/>
            <p>But the Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the affairs of the World, nor being ignorant how he ought to treat with a Sovereign Prince, went not ſo haſtily to work, and preſs'd not ſo much to undertake a Prince who had merited ſo well from the holy Chair, nor however, at leaſt, for no other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject but a woman, he well knowing that the Duke was not the onely Adulterer, and that that buſine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> would reflect upon many Princes who lived in the ſame diſorder, and therefore he gave not much ear to the Cardinal <hi>Leomelini,</hi> no more than to the other Cardinals, who undertook this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Pope, not for any hate they had to the Duke, but becauſe they were ſet on by this Cardinal.</p>
            <p>The Pope at laſt ſeeing himſelf preſſed, and not to be wanting in his duty of Paſtour, ordered the Cardinal grand Penetencier, to write to <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roglio,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caſal,</hi> that he ſhould proceed againſt the Counteſs by the ordinary wayes in the like caſes, that is to ſay, to refuſe her the Communion at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and in caſe that ſhe ſought not to mend and change her life, to put
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:154259:74"/>an end to that great ſcandal, after he had given her all thoſe fatherly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, to which his charge oblig'd him, he ſhould proceed to Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, or the other Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, which the Councils com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to be uſed in ſuch kind of Caſes.</p>
            <p>The Penetencier fail'd not to obey the order that vas given him to write, but not in the manner which the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Leomelini</hi> deſired, becauſe he writ to that Prelate in gentle terms, commanding to behave himſelf in this affair with great Prudence, with a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table zeal, which did not ſute with the deſigns and deſires of that Eminence. The Biſhop had no ſooner received that Letter, but he communicated it to the Duke and the Counteſs, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided it, and the more, becauſe the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop himſelf laught at it too, who would not do any thing againſt the pleaſure of two perſons, who had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him his Biſhoprick.</p>
            <p>This Prelate taking his leave at the end of that diſcourſe, the Duke taking him by the hand ſaid in his ear, <hi>My Lord, write to the Cardinal Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentier,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:154259:74"/>That when the Pope Chaſes all the Bawdy-Houſes out of</hi> Rome, <hi>we will drive the Counteſs from hence.</hi> It is true, he ſaid that more to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ally with the Biſhop, then for any other reaſon, becauſe he knew very well, that thoſe words would not go ſo far as <hi>Rome;</hi> though, as I believe, he had not much car'd, or not at all if they had; nay, if they had been told to his Holineſs.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop return'd a Letter to <hi>Rome</hi> full of good and ſolid choice Reaſons, which ſhew'd the neceſſity there was for the good of the Church, that they ſhou1d ſhut their eyes to thoſe diſorders, not to enrage the Duke, for if they did ſo, he fear'd he might do worſe, and might proceed to trouble and puniſh the repoſe of the Clergy; in effect, he was not deceiv'd, for if ever it had happen'd that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs had receiv'd that diſcontent, of being ſtruck by any cenſure of the Church; the Duke, who would alſo have lookt upon himſelf as injur'd, had without doubt moleſted the Clergy and the Biſhop; for Princes never want Reaſon to make Criminals: and ſince Eccleſiaſtical Men will not acknowledg
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:154259:75"/>themſelves Subjects to them, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the Biſhops, who look upon themſelves as exempt from owning that Title; but, it is a great abuſe, and they deceive themſelves groſly.</p>
            <p>The Anſwer of this Prelate hapned, I know not by which way, to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to the Cardinal <hi>Leomelini,</hi> who preſently began to murmur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Biſhop, as he did againſt the Duke, not ſparing him, even in the Conſiſtory of the Cardinals; and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the ill things he could of him, though falſly: For to ſpeak truth, this Prelate had alwayes behaved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf like an honeſt man, and has no vices that are worthy of reproches.</p>
            <p>What diſſimulation ſoever the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father ſhew'd, yet he was neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſenſibly touched with the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements he everyday received of the Scandalous Life of the Duke and the Counteſs; and therefore mov'd with Zeale and Compaſſion, he made many Prayers be offered in every Church, to the end, that it would pleaſe God to touch the Heart of that Prince, and draw him from his obſtinate hardneſs of heart, in going on in ſo infamous a
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:154259:75"/>Sin as that was, in which he had ſo long liv'd.</p>
            <p>But at laſt, making reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the duty he was oblig'd to, as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Paſtor of the Church, he ſaw well, that to hold his Peace, would not be to acquit himſelf well: on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide alſo, as he would not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in that buſineſs with rigor againſt that Prince; he reſolved, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated with his Duty and his Fear, to employ the moſt gentle remedies, and to imploy in them Perſons alſo vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, indowed with Piety.</p>
            <p>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to that purpoſe, the Father <hi>Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mantua</hi> and <hi>Caſal;</hi> he was a Perſon celebrated as well for the fairneſs of his carriage, as the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of his vertue; with Fatherly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions ſetting before him the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice he ſhould do both to God and the Church, and that he ſhould Merit ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much from the Holy Chair, if he could overcome the Spirit of this Duke, and obtain any Victory over that of the Counteſs, to make them leave off this Scandalous Life, ſo much to the Scandal of the whole Church.</p>
            <p>This good Father <hi>Capuchin,</hi> gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:154259:76"/>the hardneſs of the hearts of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterers, felt in himſelf ſome repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for this Imployment, deſpairing of ever conquering the Obſtination of the Duke, or to move his heart, which Sin had made harder then a Diamond; nevertheleſs, without reply to the Pope, he received that Commiſſion which his Holineſs impos'd upon him, with a ready and as humble obedience which belongs to that Order of <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins,</hi> and is ſo ſutable to their Habit; in a word, with a <hi>Capuchins</hi> Obedience, and with Promiſes, To do all in his Power to ſerve his Holineſs and the Church faithfully, he would ſpare no Cares to procure the Salvation of the Soules of the Duke and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs.</p>
            <p>The Pope, in giving this good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Bleſſing, commanded him, that if peradventure he perceived that his Charitable Remonſtrances, and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Corrections had no effect, and that by mild wayes he ſhould work nothing upon the Heart of that Prince, that he ſhould proceed to ſome kind of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and Threatning, in the behalfe of the Holy Chair; and yet withal that
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:154259:76"/>he ſhould not fail to let the goodneſs of the Pope be known, and to excuſe him to the Duke, if they came ſo far as to Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures againſt his Perſon.</p>
            <p>This Father went from <hi>Rome</hi> with this Order, drawing towards <hi>Mantua;</hi> but, in paſſing by <hi>Bologne,</hi> he commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated all theſe Orders he had receiv'd from His Holineſs to the Superior of a Convent of his Order in that Town, and asking his Counſel, How he ſhould Act, in an Affair of ſo great Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? they conſult together, and both concluded, That it would be better to ſtay for the opportunity of the Dukes being at <hi>Caſal,</hi> to the end, that he might have the convenience of aſſaulting both their Hearts together; our <hi>Capuchin</hi> followed this advice, and in ſtead of continuing on his way for <hi>Mantua,</hi> drew towards <hi>Caſal,</hi> where he arrived two dayes ſooner then the Duke, who came thither with the greateſt part of the Court.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Capuchin</hi> being then arrived at <hi>Caſal,</hi> diſcover'd to almoſt the whole Convent the occaſion of his Voyage, and pray'd them to joyn their Prayers
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:154259:77"/>to his, to obtain from God a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſucceſs in ſo difficult and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous an enterpriſe; but that policy of his ſucceeded very ill, contrary to his wiſhes, becauſe the plot being diſcover'd, the Noiſe of the Subject of his Voyage to <hi>Caſal</hi> was ſpread through the whole Town, ſo that he was diſcover'd before the Duke gave him the Hearing; but at laſt his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs coming alſo to be inform'd, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid every body to ſuffer this <hi>Capuchin</hi> to come near his Perſon, and not permit him to enter in any place where he was; which this poor Father per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, deſpairing of acquitting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his Commiſſion, and the more becauſe he was told, That the Duke was going ſuddenly to <hi>Mantua;</hi> he thought it neceſſary to take his Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Rome,</hi> following the Advice given him by the Lord <hi>Miroglio</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>All the World had great reſpect for this proceeding of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo much the more, becauſe it had imploy'd thoſe of the Order of <hi>Capu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins,</hi> which is in great veneration in <hi>Italy;</hi> nevertheleſs that hindred not
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:154259:77"/>the Duke, and the Counteſs, to mock at all they did to ſtifle their Love, which became greater and greater; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Proverb good, That priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion begets Apetite; becauſe the more they ſaw themſelves moleſted, upon the Subject of their Amours, the more it inflam'd in them the deſire to do all things, that could contribute, in any ſort, to their Delights, and what pleas'd them.</p>
            <p>The Duke was inform'd of all they ſaid at <hi>Rome,</hi> touching his Love to the Counteſs; and, in truth, they ſpoke of it with too much ſcorn; making Libels and Satyrs, extreamly piquant, againſt his Perſon; alſo, in return, they ſpared neither the Cardinals nor the Pope himſelf in the Court of <hi>Mantua,</hi> though the Duke did what he could to ſilence them, like a good Prince as he was (for his greateſt Vice was that Adultery) ſo great was his reſpect to the Holy Chair, he would not ſuffer them in his preſence to ſpeak any thing againſt the Heads of the Church, however his Courtiers being not of his humour, it was not in his power to make them hold their peace; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:154259:78"/>their inſolence grew to that height, that there was ſeen at <hi>Rome</hi> ſome Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, in which they Challeng'd the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of that Noble City to come to <hi>Mantua,</hi> to let them ſee they would revenge the Affront they pretended to have received from them.</p>
            <p>But it is now time for us to viſit his Highneſs in his Tent, to ſee in what condition his Love is, now he is turn'd a Soldier.</p>
            <p>The good Fortune of the <hi>French</hi> had been ſo proſperous till then, that they had carryed their Victorious Armes beyond <hi>Flanders, Catalonia,</hi> and <hi>Rouſsillon;</hi> and though they had not as yet begun to ſhew themſelves of that ſide of <hi>Caracene,</hi> towards <hi>Milan,</hi> yet they took the way to be Maſters of <hi>Italy,</hi> to which that Nation ardent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſpires: The Enemies beat the Field, and rang'd ſometimes on one ſide, and then of another, upon the Banks of the River <hi>Teſino,</hi> with ſo much Liberty, they ſeem'd to be abſolute Maſters; they were commanded by the Duke of <hi>Modene,</hi> one of the great Captains of our time; and he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed with as many Captains as
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:154259:78"/>he had Soldiers; that is to ſay, they were the Valienteſt Warriours in the World; for, in truth, at that time the <hi>French</hi> were ſo eſteem'd.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Spaniards</hi> perceiving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not in a condition to oppoſe thoſe Invincible Conquerors; and, that the Affaires went but too ill in <hi>Lombardy,</hi> addreſſed themſelves to the Emperour, deſiring him to aſſiſt them in the Defence of a place which was ſo conſiderable in the Empire; this Monarch granted their requeſts the more willingly, in regard of his own intereſt there, as well as that of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> and indeed he made it appear, that the Empire was intereſſed in it, doing upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all in his power, and joyning with thoſe of that Houſe, with whom he enter'd into a very ſtrict League, to prevent the Duchy of <hi>Mantua</hi> from falling into other hands.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>Charles</hi> was to that end nominated Vicar of the Empire, and they gave him to that purpoſe the Command of an Army, that he joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> might ſtop the Progreſs of the <hi>French</hi> Arms in <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardy:</hi>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:154259:79"/>In the mean time the <hi>French</hi> thought fit (in their Councel of War) to lay Siege to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> one of the ſtrongeſt Towns in the Duchy; and although this place was very well Mann'd and defended, this reſolution nevertheleſs gave much apprehenſion to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſince it was a place of ſuch conſequence to any that could poſſeſs themſelves of it; and for that reaſon the Duke <hi>Charles</hi> thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf oblig'd in Duty to go himſelf in Perſon to aſſiſt a place ſo important to the repoſe of all <hi>Italy;</hi> after they had then order'd all things neceſſary for the ſuccour of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> he gave Order for the March of his Army; he part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to that end, from <hi>Millan,</hi> where he had been <hi>Incognito,</hi> to ſpeak with the Miniſters of <hi>Spain,</hi> not on purpoſe, but to take an occaſion of paſſing from <hi>Mantua</hi> to <hi>Montferrat,</hi> and by that means to go to <hi>Caſal,</hi> to viſit his Counteſs, who impatiently expected him.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as he ſaw her, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd his kindneſs in an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manner to her, having been abſent from her 15 dayes, ſo that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:154259:79"/>for any to ſnatch this Prince out of the Arms of that beauty in 2 dayes; notwithſtanding all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances of thoſe which were ſent to him from the Army, who exhorted him to come in all haſte to the relief of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which was going infallibly to be loſt, if there were not ſome kind of Succour ſent immediately to it.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs had taken a reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of putting her ſelf in the Habit of a Man, and to follow the Duke whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he went; and although the Duke ſeem'd to conſent to it at firſt, yet he thought it not very convenient in the end, and therefore ſhe ſaw her ſelf ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to remain at <hi>Caſal,</hi> having obtain'd a promiſe from her Lover, That every day ſhe ſhould receive from him an Account of his health, and the progreſs of his Highneſs with that of his Army.</p>
            <p>This Prince parted from <hi>Caſal</hi> then the fourth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> accompanied with his Counteſs, who went with him in his Coach above three Miles; and alſo, by an exceſs of Gallantry, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Brother drove the Coach till they came to a certain Village, where
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:154259:80"/>they ſtopt to take leave of his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; who, drawing apart his Well-beloved, was ſometime in converſation with her, but not ſatisfied with that, and what he had injoy'd of her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany all the way, they enter'd into a Peaſants houſe hard by that place, were they were together a full hour, to the great heart-breaking of all the World, who waited for them in the Street, although in the mean while the Counteſſes Brother invented all he could imagine to divert the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>After theſe two Lovers had given their adiews to each other, having fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed all their Ceremonies in the Chamber of that good poor Country-mans houſe, they went out, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet not able to ſeparate for good and all, they ſtaid at the door, talking together, toying and fooling with one another, and alſo to make Love half an hour longer, whil'ſt in the mean time there arrived a Poſt from the Marquiſs of <hi>Faenſaldagnia,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our of <hi>Milan,</hi> who earneſtly deſir'd his Highneſs, That he would haſten his depart to the Army, where they
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:154259:80"/>impatiently waited for him, having abſolute need of his preſence: who ever had ſeen the Duke and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs ſo ſtrictly imbrac'd, would have thought they were never to meet again, and if a Gentleman a great friend of the Dukes had not confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told his Highneſs that the night came on apace, and that it was not ſafe for him to enter in the dark into a Countrey that was the rendezvous of the enemy, I believe the Duke and his Counteſs would have ſtaid a good while longer in that place, which yet was not a very convenient one, to make love in. In fine, after that theſe two Lovers had given ſome tears to their future abſence, they took leave of one another; She returning to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal,</hi> and the Duke marching towards <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where the Army ſtaid for him, and where the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Council of War was held, to conſult upon the way to ſecure that place ſo conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to their State, and which they already believed out of their power.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs of <hi>Faenſaldagnia</hi> had commanded an apartement for the Duke to be made ready in a Palace,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:154259:81"/>a mile from <hi>Alexandria,</hi> about which was encamped the Imperial and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Army, as being a very advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Poſt to trouble the enemy, who had no defence from their ſhot, and were blockt up between the Town and the River.</p>
            <p>The Duke was ſcarce arrived, but finding that Air unwholſome for him, and being very much heated by the journey, he was preſently ſeiz'd by a Feaver, which obliged him to go to bed, but that which added to his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, was to ſee himſelf in a Countrey ſo prejudicial to his health, and where he could not have thoſe things fit for his cure, with that diligence which his diſeaſe required, <hi>Tortona</hi> being diſtant from him two miles, and that was the neereſt Town wherein there were Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries.</p>
            <p>Two things begun to trouble his mind and raiſe his ſpleen and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly, The one was that ſuch a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune happened to him in the Firſt time of his life that he had appear'd in the field, fearing it would oblige him to return to <hi>Caſal,</hi> without the glory of having done any thing to ſhew
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:154259:81"/>his courage; but that which was his greateſt heart-breaking was, That he fancied the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would believe him a Coward, under which notion he ſhould paſs for ſuch through all thoſe Countries, not being able to imagine they would be ſo civil to lay all the fault upon his Feaver, (which really was the cauſe) but would rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it a fair pretence of the Dukes to hide his cowardly heart. The ſecond thing which ſo tormented him, was, To ſee himſelf alone, and deprived of the ſervice of his Counteſs, as he had been formerly: he reſolved to keep his bed notwithſtanding, and ſtay in that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace which they had provided for him, becauſe he would not looſe the ſight of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who came to viſit him (whilſt his Feaver thus perplext him,) and adviſed with him of the means the moſt fit to enterprize ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing upon the enemy.</p>
            <p>This ſickneſs of the Dukes was not carried ſo cloſe but that it came to the ears of the Counteſs, who was not a little troubled at it, and, as I believe, it was his Highneſs that advertiſed her of it, being confident that ſhe would not
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:154259:82"/>fail to come to him as ſoon as ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd that news. It was that which the Duke deſired with greateſt paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for being without his Miſtreſs he was without his heart, as he himſelf aſſur'd her brother, who writ word of it to the Counteſs, by the expreſs command of the Duke.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as the news of the Dukes ſickneſs arrived at <hi>Caſal,</hi> the Counteſs was ſo afflicted, that one would have thought ſhe had no life left, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they did what they could to perſwade her his diſeaſe was not great nor dangerous; ſhe nevertheleſs grieved very much, but ſhe grew deſperate when ſhe was inform'd that the French Army were ſo much up and down the Countrey, that it was dangerous tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling between <hi>Caſal</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> whither ſhe would go notwithſtanding accompanied with onely very few on Foot, through by-wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, with inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſerve as Phyſitian to this Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſick man, ſhe ſent out a Scout be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her journey, to be perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of the march of the enemies; that ſo ſhe might the better chuſe what way to take.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:154259:82"/>
            <p>She was uncertain in her reſolutions in what habit to travel in, whether that of her own ſex or of a man; fearful of being known if ſhe ſhould make that journey in her ordinary dreſs; but having ask'd Counſel of her Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in that affair, he adviſed her to go with very few in her company, and to diſguiſe her ſelf like a man.</p>
            <p>The reſolution for parting then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken, after the Scout ſhe ſent was return'd, which was the ſame day that the Duke himſelf had inform'd her of his being ill; ſhe diſcover'd her deſign to the Counteſs <hi>Lovize</hi> her ſiſter a little before ſhe went, this Counteſs <hi>Lovize</hi> having formerly tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd as a man with a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> whom I ſpoke of before, who was her Gallant, offer'd her ſelf now to accompany her ſiſter in the ſame poſture.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs <hi>Magaret</hi> received this offer of her ſiſters very willingly, and was the more inclined to it, by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving they two were ſo much of a humour as to matter of journeys as well as other things; ſo away they went very late in the evening accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied onely with their younger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:154259:83"/>and one man, to avoid the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter of the French, who coſted up and down the Countrey every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They went out of the great rode, croſſing the Fields by little by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paths, that were very much about, and made their journey much longer than the way they quitted had done, but as ill luck would have it, they met with what they avoided, and fell into the ſnare they took ſuch pains to avoid.</p>
            <p>They reſted at night in a Village a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle way off S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Saviour,</hi> without making themſelves known to their hoſt, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to continue their way towards <hi>Alexandria</hi> very early in the Morning; but they were deceived, as the Proverb ſayes, <hi>He that reckons without his Hoſt muſt reckon twice.</hi> For it was ſcarce two hours within night, when there arrived twelve <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cavaliers, (perhaps the Hoſt himſelf had been their Spie) who, pretending to be French-men, aſſaulted the Inne where our amorous Pilgrims were lodg'd. Theſe enemies came with ſo great a noiſe one would have thought they had been the whole French army; the poor Earl, who had
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:154259:83"/>accompanied his ſiſters, not having been accuſtomed to the noiſes of War, and ſuch kind of aſſaults as that, being afraid of his life, got up all trembling to the higheſt Garret of the houſe to hide himſelf, thinking the very Flyes were Horſes, and believing every Horſe was a compleat Army of the enemies.</p>
            <p>In the mean time theſe two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſes, diſguiz'd like men, were not yet got into bed, and ſtaid ſtill in the Chamber, almoſt in deſpair, yet the Counteſs <hi>Lovize</hi> rais'd her ſelf a little out of her Fear, when ſhe heard them ſpeak French, having been us'd to men of that Nation, though in quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Friends and not enemies, were thoſe ſhe had formerly convers'd with, which theſe Souldiers pretended not to be.</p>
            <p>Theſe brave Cavaliers were not much troubled to find out that theſe aſſieged perſons were Females and not Males, as their habits ſpoke them; and it was the better for the Ladies that it was ſo, becauſe that after they had given them the divertizement of a two hours ſiege, they went away betimes in the Morning to ſeek ſome other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:154259:84"/>and left our Fair gueſts at Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without ſuffering any damage from them at all, unleſs it were ſome few kiſſes which they were oblig'd to give them, and ſome other little rudeneſſes they offer'd them, which need not be explain'd to the Reader.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs <hi>Margaret</hi> was not a little mortified to be ſurprized by ſuch an aſſault as this, but on the contrary, the Counteſs <hi>Lovize</hi> was over-joyed in having gain'd the affection of thoſe beſiegers, and had diverted her ſelf with thoſe Counterfeit enemies, as may very well be imagin'd.</p>
            <p>They went on their journey early in the Morning, towards <hi>Alexandria,</hi> although the Earl their brother ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd them to return to <hi>Caſal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly theſe illuſtrious travellers wanted Conduct, to truſt themſelves in a journey without any train in the time of war, and in a Countrey that ſwarm'd with Souldiers, not being ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant that the enemies rang'd every where, even to the very Gates of <hi>Caſal,</hi> two cauſes nevertheleſs excus'd them, Love and Curioſity; for in effect, there was nothing but the Love of the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:154259:84"/>Counteſs <hi>Margaret</hi> to her Gallant, and the diſhoneſt curioſity of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs <hi>Louize</hi> her Siſter, which made them hazard that little honour they had left; For certainly, if they would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded a Convoy for their ſafety, they ſhould not have been deny'd it; but, who is ignorant that Love is blind, and alwayes in haſt.</p>
            <p>The Counteſs <hi>Margaret</hi> intended to relate this rencounter to the Duke, but her Brother and siſter thought it not very convenient, leaſt it might give ſome jealous trouble to that ſick Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and therefore this paſt under Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
            <p>At laſt, being come to their Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys end, into the Dukes preſence, who was in Bed, they did not trouble themſelves with great Preamble and Ceremonies, nor to keep him in long diſcourſes; but their firſt converſation was Embraces with all imaginable ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, which ſhe gave to this poor ſick man, who return'd the ſame to his Miſtreſs (whoſe heart was pierc'd with griefe) although the Room was fill'd with many Captains, and ſome of the principal of the Army.</p>
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:154259:85"/>
            <p>The Counteſs ſcarce had begun her Careſſes to the Duke, but he ſeem'd much amended, and ſo much, that he lookt like one that never had been Sick and alſo all that day he had no Feaver; which made it believed, that the Counteſs had brought ſome Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote with her to drive away the Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her Lover.</p>
            <p>The General of the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry, who was by the Duke when this Beauty enter'd the Chamber, taking leave preſently of his Highneſs, in going to the Dore, ſaid to one of his Friends who was in the Company, <hi>We may very well take leave now, and go our wayes, for the Duke will be no more for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Almoſt all the Commanders of the Army did nothing but grumble in the Camp at the Counteſſes coming thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; believing, that as long as the Duke had this Woman with him, he would forget his duty.</p>
            <p>But, for all that, they found them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves happily deceiv'd, becauſe the Duke recover'd as he was, though perhaps not altogether cur'd, by the ſight of the Counteſs, gave himſelf
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:154259:85"/>up in good earneſt to the exerciſe of his Charge.</p>
            <p>It was a ſtrange amazing ſight, to ſee this Prince ride round about his Camp on Horſeback with his Miſtreſs, giving the neceſſary Orders to his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, where he did wonders, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his firſt time of Appearance in the Field; ſo that there was very few perſons that did refuſe him the Honour he had Merited, of delivering <hi>Alexandria;</hi> he knew ſo well how to make his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of time and place, that the Beſieged became in a little time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers themſelves; and fill'd with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame feares, thoſe, who had been the moſt likely as Enemies as Beſiegers, to have given a mortal apprehenſion to his whole Army. The Duke forbore not for all this, to give the beſt part of his time to his Amours with the Counteſs, his Ague being turn'd to a Tertian, which gave him ſome reſpit, but this alteration made it the more dangerous.</p>
            <p>And ſince theſe Ladies had not brought with them Cloaths ſutable to their Sex, they preſently ſent away an expreſs to furniſh them; it being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:154259:86"/>unpleaſant to the Duke to ſee her who poſſeſt his heart, under any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit but her own; not at all caring to ſee her dreſt like a Man as well in the Chamber, as in the Camp, whither he often carry'd her.</p>
            <p>As for what belong'd to the vertue of the Counteſs <hi>Louize,</hi> ſhe loſt not one hour of the day by idleneſs, her great pleaſure being to receive the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits of the Chief Commanders in that Army, amongſt whom ſhe paſs'd her time with ſuch ſatisfaction, that ſhe often loſt her ſelf, ſo that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for her Siſter to find her; it being certain that ſhe had above half a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Favourites, who fai'd not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent her to their power; and for that reaſon a certain <hi>Florentine</hi> Gentleman, who, as well as the greateſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, had received from the Counteſs <hi>Louize</hi> ſome Favours, told a Comrade of his, That he found the Whores of <hi>Caſal</hi> very obliging.</p>
            <p>The Newes of the Arrival of this Lady into the Camp, and of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty which ſhe afforded every one, to offer her their Service, as well as the goodneſs ſhe had ſhew'd to that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:154259:86"/>we mention'd before, quickly ſpread it ſelf into the <hi>French</hi> Camp, ſo that it afforded the beſt ſport in the World: and there was a perſon, who, diſcourſing with the Duke of <hi>Modena</hi> of this Fair Curtiſan, ſaid, in deriſion of her, <hi>Li Frances, Fanno Le Puttane, egli ſpagnoli le godono;</hi> The <hi>French</hi> create the Whores, and the <hi>Spaniards</hi> injoy them.</p>
            <p>This he ſaid in reflection upon her firſt Gallantry with the <hi>French</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur, which I have already told you of.</p>
            <p>In fine, The <hi>French</hi> Army rais'd the Siege from before <hi>Alexandria</hi> in the night, the 16th. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> after they had beſieged it three Moneths; and they diſlodg'd themſelves with ſo little noiſe, and ſo ſecretly, that their Enemies themſelves that were round about them perceived it not until morning after the Sun was up; and that from the Town Walls there was no Tents, nor any thing elſe to be ſeen.</p>
            <p>The News was preſently carryed to the Duke, who was yet in Bed with his Goddeſs; he expreſſed no ſmall
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:154259:87"/>diſpleaſure of this unexpected depart of his Enemies, chiefly having reſolved to give them Battel the day following, believing, the Victory would certainly have been his, if he could have once dſiputed it with them.</p>
            <p>So, as ſoon as he was up, he went to viſit the Batteries that the <hi>French</hi> had made againſt the Town, having no body in his company but his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs; her Siſter, the Counteſs <hi>Louize</hi> being gone in other Company; they ſtaid nine dayes at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and in the evening of the laſt day the Duke went away, accompanied by ſome of the chief Commanders amongſt the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and after he had given the neceſſary Orders for the conſervation of that place, and recommended the care of the Army to his Lieutenant, he return'd to <hi>Caſal</hi> with his Lady.</p>
            <p>The joy of his arrival at <hi>Caſal</hi> was Celebrated, that Town indeavouring to ſhew him all the Honour imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, in acknowledgment, that they lookt upon him as the Deliverer of a place of that importance; but, after all, thoſe Feaſts were kept with much modeſty.</p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:154259:87"/>
            <p>The greateſt pleaſure of the Duke, was, to paſs the beſt and greateſt part of the day in going here and there with the Counteſs thinking no mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the Army than of any thing elſe, to the great aſtoniſhm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt of all the World; who could not enough ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, how a Man could be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o much devoted to the love of that Woman, for he was quite contrary to other men, who love change<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and often turn their backs, not only to Whores, but even to their Wives, after they have Marry'd them: My dear Reader, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thou very well underſtandeſt me, and that it is not neceſſary I ſhould explain my ſelf further, and therefore I will only tell thee, That this Prince, the more he injoy'd his Well-Beloved, the more his deſire was kindled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her; and in the Mornings, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n he roſe out of bed he was mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately in Love with her, then at night when he went to bed to this Count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs; the Fire of his Amorous paſſion was te-kindled at thoſe times that othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s make uſe of for their repoſe.</p>
            <p>From that time the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uke fail'd not one day of that Summer to V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſit
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:154259:88"/>his Counteſs at her own houſe, and when they were alone they made no ſcruple to pull off their Cloaths, and go to Bed together, without any more Complements; The one, as if he were a Prince without a Principality; the other, as if ſhe were one of thoſe Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizans of <hi>Rome,</hi> that are alwayes in their Smockes waiting for their <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves.</hi> And although the Duke did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten force himſelf to give Audience to all the World that came to his Court, yet it was in ſuch a way, it was eaſily ſeen that he did it with <hi>Chagrin,</hi> and againſt his mind, and carry'd himſelf like an extravagant; and it is not hard for me to believe it, ſince that all his thoughts, his ſoul and heart breath'd nothing elſe but his love of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs.</p>
            <p>But, for to give more convincing Proofes of this, and to aſſure the whole World, and chiefly his own Subjects, that the Counteſs was abſolutely his, and poſſeſt all his Affections, he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed her two Men for Guards, who wore the ſame Livery of his own Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, with order to follow this Lady whereever ſhe went, and to Guard
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:154259:88"/>her Houſe night and day; this ſo publick teſtimony of the Dukes love, made her be reſpected, and more eſteem'd than ever, and alſo fear'd by every one, ſo much it would have been lookt upon as Sacriledge, to have given her the leaſt diſpleaſure, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content; and there were at that time four perſons condemn'd to Baniſhment for having their Tongues a little too long, and had talk'd too lewdly againſt this beloved Lady.</p>
            <p>There was alſo another had the like ill Fortune, but he rather out of Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, then for any thing elſe; hearing the Barrenneſs of the Counteſs talk'd on, who had no Children, neither by her Husband, nor the Duke, began to laugh, and ſaid, <hi>Che non Faceva Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialli, Perche voleva eſſer troppo ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This poor Babler carry'd not his words to Purgatory, for they put him in Priſon for ſome dayes, and he had ſtaid there longer, but for the Interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that perſon whom he chiefly had offended by his words, and was not inclin'd to Revenge, although what had been ſaid had not much pleas'd her.</p>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:154259:89"/>
            <p>Certainly that Lady deſerv'd the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of ſo great a Prince very much, being adorn'd with all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious qualities which ſhe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd; ſhe had a way of ſpeaking ſo gentle and ſo attractive, that ſhe cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated all hearts, and oblig'd them to love her; I do not mean here of her extraordinary and charming way with which ſhe careſſed the Duke, having no expreſsions capable to deſcribe them, but ſhe was inclin'd to oblige every body, ſo it were not to injure her ſelf, nor as one may ſay, pick her own pocket, for in that caſe ſhe had no memory, being like other women, who are ſparing, not to ſay co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous; Pride never ſet his foot in her Carriage: but, on the contrary, the more ſhe ſaw her ſelf in the Princes Favour, the more did the deſire in her increaſe to Speak Familiarly with all People, and to converſe modeſtly with every one: The Balls, Feaſts, and Recreations of taking the Air, alwayes took up her thoughts, and her minde went no further then thoſe noble Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements; and nevertheleſs, when ſhe chanc'd to meet the Duke in any
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:154259:89"/>place, ſhe expreſs'd a careleſneſs of all things elſe beſides the pleaſing ſight of his perſon, which ſhe eſteem'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all; Anger nor Vanity never tranſported her; and if ſometimes ſhe had occaſion to Chide the Servants of her Houſe, ſhe did it without thoſe tranſports ſo ordinary to other Ladies; and alſo thoſe Cloaths ſhe had, ſo rich above the other Ladies of her quality in the Court, ſhe wore them without vanity, pride, or ſcorn, and contempt to thoſe that had not the like; It is true, ſhe frequented the Churches more through Cuſtome then any other reaſon; and if ſhe went to the Maſſe, it was only to be ſeen, and to ſee; Yet, I muſt tell you, that ſhe went thither ſometimes, being Invited to it on purpoſe by the Eccleſiaſtical Men, to the end of giving more Luſtre to the Solemnities, which were at that time Celebrated in the Church; and alſo to ſhew her the great eſteem they had of her Perſon, with which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs ſhe was not ſatisfied. And although ſhe had a Face Faire and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable enough, yet there is nothing very laſcivious; but, whil'ſt the Duke
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:154259:90"/>was living, when ſhe was near him, ſhe lookt upon him as if ſhe would have devour'd him with her Eyes, her looks at that time being the Effects of which, her Impudent Love was the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But, above all this, there was ſome light of Prudence ſhin'd in her carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, which appear'd in effect a Miracle, becauſe this Faire one was not like thoſe Women that affect the Trade of St. <hi>Placidia</hi> to pleaſe their Friends; that is to ſay, For all her great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the Duke, and that was ſo abſolute, ſhe could diſpoſe of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as ſhe pleas'd, without the fear of diſpleaſing him; ſhe yet kept her ſelf for all that within the bounds of an humble modeſty, giving his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thanks for all the Favours he did her; aſſuring him, That ſhe was more then ſatisfied to injoy alone the Loves of ſo great a Prince: And the more the Duke offer'd his Service to her, and deſir'd her to make uſe of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as ſhe pleas'd, the leſs did ſhe importune him with Requeſts; ſo that when the Duke preſs'd her to ask ſome Favour at his hands, ſhe uſually made
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:154259:90"/>anſwer, <hi>His Highneſs granted her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour great enough, to let her injoy his Perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all this ſhe Favour'd whom ſhe pleas'd, and who were recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her, which were without number, their being none ignorant, how great her power was with the Prince, whoſe heart ſhe poſſeſs'd, and govern'd his whole will; and, for that reaſon every one made Addreſſes to her, to help them in their Affaires, according as they needed her Favour; but, on her ſide, ſhe knew very well what kind of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſhe was to demand of his Highneſs, not to diſpleaſe him; and ſhe very rarely preſs'd him to grant any extraordinary matter, if ſhe had been of an humour to inrich her ſelf, ſhe wanted no opportunities of doing it, and the Duke would never have hinder'd her; on the contrary, he advis'd her to do it, and gave her all the meanes poſſible for it; ſo far, that when any one addreſt to himſelf to obtain a Requeſt he us'd to ſay, <hi>For that you muſt Petition none but the Counteſs and that was the onely way to obtain their end.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:154259:91"/>
            <p>That Charitable Counteſs had never yet the Repute of doing any thing out of Intereſt; but it has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes been thought, that all ſhe did was to purchaſe to her ſelf Friends, rather then through hopes of any gain, expreſſing alwayes her averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that Lucre; It is true notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that when any one offer'd her ſome Fine thing, or conſiderable Summ of Money, ſhe would do as thoſe, who, laying their hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Preſent offer'd them, uſually ſay, There is no need of this, and yet take it willingly enough.</p>
            <p>The greateſt care of this Lady, and what ſhe ſought after with all the Paſsion imaginable, was the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of her Brother, which put the Duke to a ſtand, what more to give him; having already Honour'd him with Imployments and Offices very conſiderable, and much above his deſerts; or at leaſt if he did any way Merit them, it was very little: nevertheleſs the Counteſs never ceas'd begging for him, and could have wiſh'd her Brother rais'd above all the Princes of that Court.</p>
            <pb n="175" facs="tcp:154259:91"/>
            <p>The Arch-Ducheſs heard this news with a great heart-breaking; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the efforts of which her vertue was capable, ſhe could not hinder her ſelf from being extreamly diſpleas'd at the Advancing of that young Lord, who never had a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Merit: but, that which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d her greateſt Affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction, was, to, ſee her chiefeſt Servants rather caſt down, then rais'd in the leaſt; and us'd with ſcorn, that deſerv'd to be treated with Honour; which caus'd theſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or unfortunate Perſons to ſay, <hi>That the Duke ſhew'd more favour to the Brother of an Adulterous Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, then to the Servants of a Princeſs his lawful and true Wife:</hi> and amongſt other things, witneſs many Libels and Satyrs, which I omit.</p>
            <p>Although this innocent Princeſs receiv'd ſome kind of Mortification from all this, however ſhe never had a reſentment againſt the Duke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the firſt place ſhe plainly ſaw, that he did nothing out of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, but only to ſatisfie that blind paſſion, which had inſlav'd him in the Chaines of that Concubine: And
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:154259:92"/>Secondly, ſhe eſteem'd it not juſt nor reaſonable to compare theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, perſons of great Merit, with that Earle, that was a Man of no Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>In the mean time this Counteſs poſſeſt all the Favour of this Prince, and kept alone the two Keys of his Treaſures; That of his Heart, by Love, injoying him without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption: and the other, his Favours; ſince the Duke was ſo well pleas'd when his Miſtriſs made any Requeſt to him; that ſhe, knowing him of that humour, made pretenſions to him only for his ſatisfaction, as it is eaſily to be known by this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter following.</p>
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:154259:92"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My little Heart!</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CAEſar</hi> comes to tell me, that thou haſt an intention to ask ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of me, in behalf of a Perſon that addreſs'd to thy Courteſie, and becauſe thou wert apprehenſive of diſpleaſing me, thou didſt not mention it yeſterday in the afternoon, that we were together. This way of thine of being baſhful, makes me believe that thou doſt not love me: for certainly, if thou didſt love me, thou wouldeſt act as freely with me, as I do with thee; alſo if I had ever yet refuſed thee any thing, I confeſs thou mighteſt with reaſon ask me nothing: but ſince I am ſo glad to grant thee all things, why art thou unwilling to ask me any thing? To what end is Love painted blind and naked, if it is not to teach Lovers Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity one with the other? The Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipality is mine, and I am thine, but the authority is common to us both, that is to ſay, thou maiſt make uſe of me, and I of the State; if thou loveſt me then ask, command, and love thy</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Charles.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:154259:93"/>
            <p>But notwithſtanding all theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations and Teſtimonies of love from the Duke, this Fair One would never importune him by asking any favour that would bring the leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet to his Highneſs, having wit enough to diſcern between thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſhe was to ask for his conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and thoſe ſhe was to demand for her ſelf. That for which ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portun'd him the moſt, and rung in his ears from Morning until night, was, That he would carry her every where with him; and not being pleas'd with ſtaying ſo long at <hi>Caſal,</hi> deſiring to go into the Countrey, and which was worſt of all, ſhe would not go that journey, unleſs the Duke went with her. The Duke having at that time at Fancy to ſee <hi>Gennes,</hi> ſhe begun to ſecond it, and to ſolicite his Highneſs by all kind of Supplications, not ſparing all the flatteries and courtſhips imaginable, to make him condeſcend to her deſire, who was already her ſlave of Love, which ſhe held in chains, ſhe met with no ſmall repugnance, nay much more than ſhe found when ſhe was diſputing
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:154259:93"/>with him concerning her journey to <hi>Venice,</hi> which, nevertheleſs the Duke had made chiefly upon her conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding ſhe got the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, and according as ſhe deſired they parted from <hi>Caſal</hi> in the beginning of <hi>July</hi> with a very ſmall train, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcovering his Highneſſes deſigns to any, he made as though he would go to <hi>Mantua,</hi> not letting it be known which way he would go.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Genoiſes</hi> did not a little wonder to hear of the arrival of this Prince in their Town but more to ſee him there, ſince he was there before they could hear of his intentions of coming to that place, and there were many that would not believe that the Duke was come thither in ſo unſeaſonable a time, and without any buſineſs there; but when they ſaw him accompanied with his Counteſs, they laid aſide their wonder, all the world believing that that journey was made for the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction alone of that Favorite, who had certainly a curioſity to ſee that Town, which eſteem'd one of
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:154259:94"/>the moſt curious that is to be ſeen.</p>
            <p>The Senate, following its ordinary generoſity, received the Duke with all the demonſtrations of Love that they are accuſtomed to pay to Princes, who travel <hi>incognito,</hi> and regal'd him with a great number of ſweet-meats and other refreſhments, and beſides that honour, he received many viſites from publike as well as private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but to ſay the truth, the Duke not going thither to no other end but to divert the Counteſs, and ſatisfie her deſires, he was not very glad to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portun'd by all theſe viſites, it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing convenient for either of them to receive thoſe Civilities, and therefore to many it was ſaid, the Duke was not in his Lodging, and it was no great Lye for thoſe few dayes he ſtaid in that Town, which ſcarce amounted to three days, he did nothing elſe but go up and down with his Beloved, whom he led by the hand, followed by the Counteſs <hi>Lovize</hi> her ſiſter, and two other Ladies who came to keep her
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:154259:94"/>company, which were alſo led by the Courtiers.</p>
            <p>Two things appear'd ſtrange to the inhabitants of <hi>Genes:</hi> The firſt was the Dukes entring into a Church to hear Maſs, kneel'd upon one ſtep with the Counteſs, to whom he did nothing but talk from the beginning to the end, as one may ſay, From <hi>L'introibo</hi> until <hi>Deo gratias, de L' in principio,</hi> which made ſome ſay, That the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of that Prince conſiſted in words and not in deeds. The ſecond thing ſo extraordinary to the people was, That when he went to ſee the Palace, he ſtill led the Counteſs by the hand, as if he had been her Squire; but for my part I do not think that ſuch a wonder, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe though he led her in publike places, yet there was not ſo much cauſe for wonder, to ſee him lead her in a place where ſhe was not to be ſeen by ſo many. There was at that time at <hi>Genes,</hi> an woman Cavalier, who one day diſcourſing with ſome of that Town concerning the Ladies that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the Duke, or rather, whom the Duke followed, and amongſt the reſt
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:154259:95"/>ſpeaking of the licentious diſorder'd Life and Carriage of the Counteſs <hi>Lovize,</hi> happened to ſay, When the Duke ſhall have diſhonour'd the reſt of you <hi>Monſieurs</hi> of <hi>Genes,</hi> he will poſſibly drive away all the Cows to <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Genois,</hi> who was as witty as pleaſant, made him this reparty, <hi>I aſſure you that his Highneſs ſhall do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe I know for certain that the Romans love the Calves better than the Cows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame day the Duke went from <hi>Genes,</hi> there were two Father <hi>Capuchins,</hi> the moſt famous in all the Province, who had undertaken to accompliſh that which the Father <hi>Catori</hi> could not, and who demanded Audience of his Highneſs, pretending they had Orders from <hi>Rome</hi> to ſpeak to him, preſs'd on to that, as ſome thought, by the Cardinal <hi>Durazzo,</hi> archbiſhop of <hi>Genes,</hi> a Perſon of a ſingular goodneſs, whoſe Zeal has not onely edified thoſe of his Church, but of all the World.</p>
            <p>But the Counteſs gueſſing very well
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:154259:95"/>for what thoſe good Fathers came for, and what was their deſign, that ſhe left not the Duke a moment, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs becauſe they were ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate to ſpeak with the Duke in private, ſaying, That they had great things to communicate to him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Perſon and State; The Counteſs was forc'd to withdraw, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Duke in the Chamber with the <hi>Capuchins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The diſcourſe which theſe good Fathers had with the Duke was full of holy Zeal, and they ſpake with ſo much tenderneſs, that one of them melted into tears; at every word, they conjur'd him in the Name of God, to forſake this ſcandalous life, which he led before all his Subjects, or, to ſay rather, in the ſight of all the World; they added further, that, The Pope himſelf had wept many times, and that his clemency once being at an end, he ſhould be oblig'd then to proceed to other Courſes. They forgot nothing to inſpire into him ſome Chriſtian Sentiments of Heaven and Hell, and they let him ſee the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:154259:96"/>impoſſibility there was to attain to the firſt, whilſt he led this diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd and licentious life, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility of his falling into the other. They alleadg'd to him many Places out of the holy Scripture, which they pointed out to him, to let him ſee that the ſins of the Prince was often a cauſe of God's puniſhing the people, by an infinite number of Miſeries, Warres, and Plagues. In fine, they ſet before him al the moſt ſolid and ſtrong Reaſons, that their Wits could fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them with, not ſparing for complaints, and threats from the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> proteſting to him that if his Highneſs did not alter his Courſe of life, that Court was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to proceed againſt him by the wayes of Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures the moſt ſevere. Briefly, they were not niggardly of all that a true Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with which they were animated, could ſuggeſt to them, to make the Duke quit his love to the Counteſs, and deliver himſelf from that ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſlavery that had kept him ſo long a time in bondage.</p>
            <pb n="185" facs="tcp:154259:96"/>
            <p>During the Converſation of theſe holy Fathers with the Duke, the Counteſs was hearkning at the door, where ſhe could hear every word di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly: ſhe was in deſpair, with the fear that the Duke ſhould yield at laſt to all theſe Councels of theſe Fathers; he heard them with much Patience, without ſaying the leaſt word, till at laſt, weary of hearing them longer, and to hear the inſolent reproaches, which they made him, he anſwer'd them, <hi>That they had Chaſtity in their Convent, and at</hi> Rome <hi>the Cardinals had Wenches, and the eonvenience of diverting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and therefore he did not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at their ſpeaking to him in that manner.</hi> And as one of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed ſomething that toucht the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the Counteſs, who, as I have already ſaid, was behind the door, ſhe came into the room, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted their diſcourſe, and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſpeak low, ſhe ſaid to the Duke, ſo that theſe good Fathers heard her well enough,</p>
            <pb n="186" facs="tcp:154259:97"/>
            <q>Send theſe Fathers to the Convent, and for us let us go to <hi>Caſal.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>After that his Highneſs taking his well-beloved by the hand, began to ſay,</p>
            <q>Theſe Fathers would have Us wiſer than the Princes and Patriarchs of the old time, who had at leaſt one wife and one Concubine, not to ſpeak of a great number beſides, of both the one and the other.</q>
            <p>To which one of the <hi>Capuchins</hi> replyed,</p>
            <q>But your Higheneſs does not ſee that we are now in the times where the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel is to be obſerved, and that it is indiſputable for us, to act like <hi>Jews,</hi> now we are <hi>Catholicks.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>The Prince, touch'd to the quick by theſe words, anſwer'd them with a threatning and fierce air.</p>
            <q>My Fathers, without any other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, I will throw you out of the Window, and ſo we will uſe like <hi>Jews</hi> thoſe people that underſtand not how no treat with <hi>Catholike Princes.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Having ſaid that, he preſently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one of his Gentlemen, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:154259:97"/>them to conduct thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men out of the Palace: after that he turn'd his back upon them, and went into a Chamber with the Counteſs, who being in great wrath at theſe Fathers, proteſted in grinding her teeth, that ſhe would never give alms to a <hi>Capuchin,</hi> and ſhe did not onely ſay ſo, but do ſo, ſo that ſome people ſaid, That the taſt of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puchins</hi> of <hi>Genes</hi> had taken away the power of eating from the <hi>Capuchins</hi> of <hi>Caſal,</hi> and that theſe laſt did pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the faults thoſe others had committed.</p>
            <p>Truly if theſe holy Fathers had had to do with ſome other Prince, it might have been fear'd that they had not come off at ſo cheap a rate; but for good luck to them they ſpoke to a very good Prince, who was of no ill nature, preferr'd quiet above all things.</p>
            <p>The Duke entertain'd himſelf of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the proceeding of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puchins,</hi> in his return to <hi>Caſal,</hi> and particularly one night in the Inn at <hi>Saravalla,</hi> where he was lodg'd, he ſaid to her,</p>
            <pb n="188" facs="tcp:154259:98"/>
            <q>My Heart, if I have loved thee hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, to ſatisfie my Love which would have it ſo; I will love thee hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, to make them mad that would not have it ſo.</q>
            <p>Upon that the Counteſs taking her time, replyed, <hi>If your Highneſs ſhould ceaſe loving me, you would let people ſee you are afraid of Monks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this was done to turn the Duke from the love of this crafty woman, but in vain; for all the trouble the Monks gave themſelves, who came as Embaſſadors from <hi>Rome,</hi> ſerved for no end but to enflame the hearts of theſe two Lovers the more, for ſince the Counteſs apprehended the loſs of the Dukes favour, fearing that ſome time or other he might ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be touch'd by ſome remorſe of Conſcience, ſhe imploy'd all her Careſſes that her Love could deviſe, and ſuch Charms ſhe made uſe of, that they were aſſuredly powerful enough to have provok'd our Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf to have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſin of adultery with her, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he is a man whoſe life is
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:154259:98"/>without reproach; ſo that the Duke who was tender in his love, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be made much of, ſeemed to melt as lead in the Fire, and appear'd in that encounter as if he would have ſooner conſented to loſe his State, than his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>After that Voyage the Duke left her at <hi>Caſal,</hi> whilſt he went to <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua</hi> about ſome particular affairs, he ſaid there above a Moneth without going to ſee the Counteſs, who was ſo afflicted for not ſeeing him that poſſeſt her heart, not ſatisfied with his Letters, which ſhe received from him every week; ſhe went out very early one Morning towards <hi>Mantua,</hi> to find his Highneſs; but her good fortune haſtning her joy, ſhe met the Duke upon the way, who went with her to <hi>Caſal,</hi> renewing her careſſes, and making amends for the time loſt.</p>
            <p>Some moneths after it happened, to the great diſpleaſure of the Duke and reſentment of the Counteſs, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Copies of a Manuſcript, intituled, <hi>Whoredom,</hi> in form of Letters, under the name of an unknown Author,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:154259:99"/>were ſent to divers of the chief No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of <hi>Caſal</hi> and <hi>Mantua,</hi> and alſo into the Convents, the Duke was much troubled, being deſcrib'd there as the Prince of Whores, and chief of the bandy-houſes; and that which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd him the more was, That it ſpoke of the other Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> with Elogies and Expreſſions of reſpect. That Satyre ſaid more than it is poſſible to imagine againſt the houſe of the Counteſs, and it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſpeak with more infamy, and it was the more ſo, becauſe it min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled truth and lyes together, but in ſuch a manner, that it all lookt like truth; and certainly it was reaſonable enough, for they were a Family of Six perſons, whole life was the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of all the World. In the mean time, theſe Earls and Counteſſes had no great reaſon to be angry at what was there ſaid, if they had been Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of truth: For their houſe had for certain been a perfect bandy-houſe, there being Six Ladies in that Family who lived almoſt publikely like common Whores, I ſay, almoſt,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:154259:99"/>becauſe there were three of them who carried it with more diſcretion, which were the two wives of the brothers to the Counteſs, and one of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs <hi>Lovizes</hi> daughters, who acted their parts more privately, and yet nevertheleſs would not ſuffer a Friend to die: but as for the reſt, which were the Counteſs <hi>Margaret,</hi> and <hi>Lovize,</hi> and another of their ſiſters, kept by a <hi>Mantua</hi> Lord; they kept no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures neither in their ſpeeches nor manner of Life, ſo that they did all that they fancied was lawful, and ſo their houſe merited the name was given it.</p>
            <p>This good and jolly company were preſent with the Duke in all his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertizements, which the more anger'd all Perſons of Honour, and gave a great ſcandal to all the people of the Duchy of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and alſo to all <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Prince led this diſſolute and licentious life with the Counteſs fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen year, and ſo gave example to other Gentlemen of his Court to paſs their time with the other Ladies,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:154259:100"/>which I have told you of; ſo that with reaſon her houſe was called a bandy-houſe, there being no other diſcourſes heard there but what were impudent and diſhoneſt, every one taking a pride in ſpeaking as wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they could: This oblig'd all the other Ladies of the Town, that were of Honour and Quality to avoid this abominable Company, and fly from thoſe beaſtly women, as from the Devil of Hell; Many other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents happened to this Prince by his love to the Counteſs every day; but a hundred Pens would ſcarce be enough to recount them all: I have writ the Story of this amour but ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially, for to repeat all things would be too tedious, beſides there are many things in it which, if writ, would cauſe nothing but ſcandal.</p>
            <p>The love of the Duke was at this paſs that he delighted in nothing but the love of the Counteſs, when it pleas'd Heaven to take away that great ſcandal from the eyes of all the people, and put an end to that crime which cauſed ſo many others, by
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:154259:100"/>giving a Period to the life of him that committed it.</p>
            <p>This Prince then was taken in the beginning of <hi>September,</hi> in the Year 1665, with ſo violent a Feaver, that the firſt minute it was thought Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant by all the Phyſitians; and ſoon after, not onely dangerous, but deſperate: The Dutcheſs appear'd ſenſibly afflicted with this Sickneſs of the Dukes, and omitted nothing that ſhe thought could help him with all poſſible diligence; and which was more commendable, the aſſiſted him with all the affection of her heart; which cau'd many to ſay, <hi>That if ſhe had been in the ſame condition as the Duke her Husband was in at that time, he would not have been carry'd with ſo much heate and paſsionate care to her recovery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was Command given to all the Churches, To ſay their Prayers to God for the health of the Duke; but ſince there was no hope given on that ſide for his Recovery, he was advis'd to make his Will, which he did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly enough: And it is true, that in
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:154259:101"/>thinking of his Counteſs he ſigh'd bitterly; and, deſiring to leave her ſomething, he was ſilent a little while; after that, giving another great ſigh, he made known his Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>My Lord the Biſhop, who aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him in thoſe laſt moments of life, made him underſtand, That for the ſatisfaction and edification of his Soul, he ought to aske forgiveneſs of her Highneſs his Wife, for the Injury he had done her, to which he ſeem'd very much enclin'd; and then cauſing that Amiable Dutcheſs to come near his Bed, he embrac'd her with his left Arme, and taking her hands with his right, he ſaid to her weeping, <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, my ſoul, this minute I am come to know how much I have offended God by my Sin; and I alſo know that which I have committed in relation to you; but my Lord Biſhop, who takes a care of my Soul in this extremity, aſſures me, That I may hope or the Pardon of the good God; therefore I pray you that on your ſide alſo, you will give me ſome teſtimonies of your forgiving me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="195" facs="tcp:154259:101"/>
            <p>The Tears and Sighs of that poore Princeſs ſtopt her ſpeech, and would not let her pronounce one word; but they wrought ſo ſenſibly upon all that were preſent, that the noiſe of their Groanes and Teares, which they could not in pity refraine to ſo touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſight, was very mournful, and ſo lamentable a hearing, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſearing it might add to the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that ſick Prince, councell'd the Dutcheſs to retire; and to that end took here by the Arme and led her into another Roome, where ſhe began to weep in good earneſt.</p>
            <p>Towards the evening of that ſame day the Duke call'd for the young Prince his Son, to whom he gave his bleſsing; and after he had given him ſome Inſtructions of Living well, he concluded in theſe words; <hi>My very dear and well-beloved Son, obey your Mother, and the more, becauſe ſhe is a woman of great Vertue; and take not example from your Father, who is a great Sinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day, being the 15 of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> he paſt out of this miſerable
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:154259:102"/>Valley of Teares into the place of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Felicity, leaving the whole Court in an extraordinary ſadneſs, and almoſt inconſolable grief; the noiſe of his Death was no ſooner ſpread through the Town, but all the People was ſeen in Teares; and with reaſon, for ſet aſide his Sin, which after all that can be ſaid, proceeded from the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of humane nature, he had all the Vertues; or to ſay better, in a word, he had all qualities neceſſary to make a great Prince, and a great Monarch.</p>
            <p>He us'd his Subjects very gently, and help'd them in all things to his power; having been often heard to ſay, <hi>That he choſe rather to be a Poore Prince, and to have rich Subjects, then to have his Subjects poore, and to be himſelf a very Opulent Prince.</hi> Above all, no perſon ever went away diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented from him: He alſo recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the Judges, Mercy and Juſtice; in fine, in two Ages there had not been ſeen in <hi>Italy</hi> a Prince like him, if the Love he had for that Counteſs had not hindred him from exerciſing that goodneſs, vertue, and
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:154259:102"/>courage, which were ſo natural to him.</p>
            <p>The People wept for him, and ſhould not yet dry up their Teares, if the goodneſs of that Princeſs-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and the hopes they have in the vettue of this young Prince, the ſole Heir of the Houſe of <hi>Gonzague,</hi> and only Child to the Deceaſed Duke; which is brought up by that Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Turtle with ſo much care, did not comfort them; his vertue, his watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, aſsiduous attachments to the Government of the State, has Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiv'd the hearts of all the People, and makes him ſtill be ador'd and lov'd by all the World.</p>
            <p>The little Duke, of the Age of fourteen yeares, given no little conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Dutcheſs his Mother, and to her Subjects; and I perſwade my ſelf eaſily, that thoſe incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble qualities which begin to ſhine in his Perſon, will make his name and memory eternal amongſt thoſe Great Men, whoſe name is in Veneration.</p>
            <p>He already receives Ambaſſadors with ſo good a Grace, and with ſo much
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:154259:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="197" facs="tcp:154259:103"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:154259:104"/>ſweetneſs, that they cannot enough ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, how there can be ſo much ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and capacity in an age ſo tender.</p>
            <p>It is thought, that the Death of the Duke is like to bring no good to the Houſe of the Counteſs; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready they begin to take away thoſe Imployments with which the late Duke had Honour'd them, to the great ſatisfaction of all the World; and to ſay truth, the abaſing of that Houſe is the Subject of the Mirth of a great many; and ſo much the more, becauſe thoſe Earles, in conſideration of their Siſter <hi>Margaret,</hi> had held up their heads ſo high, that (as 'tis ſaid) they could ſcarce with the end of their Noſe touch their equalls without much difficulty.</p>
            <p>This Change will certainly be very cruel to them, and they will have much trouble to live with the young Prince, after another manner then they did with His Father; it being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry likely, that they not having been us'd to obey, they will not know how to carry themſelves to the Prince as their lawful Soveraign Lord, having accuſtom'd to treat with the late
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:154259:104"/>Duke as Familiar Friends, and not as Subjects, and therefore they have reaſon to fear, that this alteration will bring a notable change into their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, foreſeeing very well, that if that young Prince once take upon him the Government of the State, he will make them act with him after quite another manner then they did with his Father: And this is one of the Chief Reaſons why I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Story by the Death of the Duke, without ſpeaking further of the Counteſs, no more then of other things, waiting for ſome other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which we ſhall not want in time.</p>
            <p>I will not however finiſh this Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, my dear Reader, till I have told you my Thoughts, which is, that you have not taken ſo much delight in Reading it, as I did in Compoſing it; if you had been an Eye-witneſs of all that I have written, I doubt not but you alſo would have been as well pleas'd; and I know it by myſelf, who having ſeen all this Hiſtory, and all the paſſages of this Amour, I receive
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:154259:105"/>more ſatisfaction in committing it to Paper: if you have not receiv'd what you expected, or that my Style has not pleas'd you, or if by misfortune you meet with faults, I prethee think, if thou art diſcreet, that Love is blind and hath a Band upon his Eyes, ſo hard, that it is impoſſible for him to ſee either his own Faults, or that of others; I ſay of others, becauſe if you ſhould have a mind to undertake my Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, I ſhall not be of an humour to follow your Sentiments; it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces me, that I had deſign to divert you; but, if my ill Fortune has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd me of that good luck, I deſire you to arme your ſelves with patience as well as I.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:105"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:106"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:106" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:107"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154259:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
